<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The argument of Mr. Peter de la Marteliere aduocate in the Court of Parliament of Paris made in Parliament, the chambers thereof being assembled. For the Rector and Vniuersitie of Paris, defendants and opponents, against the Iesuits demandants, and requiring the approbation of the letters patents which they had obtained, giuing them power to reade and to teach publikely in the aforesaid Vniuersitie. Translated out of the French copie set forth by publike authoritie.</title>
            <title>Plaidoyé de Pierre de la Martelière ... pour le recteur et Université de Paris ... contre les Jesuites. English</title>
            <author>La Martelière, Pierre de, d. 1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04991</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108203</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843875</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04991)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 803:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The argument of Mr. Peter de la Marteliere aduocate in the Court of Parliament of Paris made in Parliament, the chambers thereof being assembled. For the Rector and Vniuersitie of Paris, defendants and opponents, against the Iesuits demandants, and requiring the approbation of the letters patents which they had obtained, giuing them power to reade and to teach publikely in the aforesaid Vniuersitie. Translated out of the French copie set forth by publike authoritie.</title>
                  <title>Plaidoyé de Pierre de la Martelière ... pour le recteur et Université de Paris ... contre les Jesuites. English</title>
                  <author>La Martelière, Pierre de, d. 1631.</author>
                  <author>Browne, George, lawyer.</author>
                  <author>Université de Paris.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 111, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By W. Hall], and are to be sold [by N. Butter] neere S. Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Plaidoyé de Pierre de la Martelière .. pour le recteur et Université de Paris, deffendeurs et opposans, contre les Jesuites.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed "G.B.". Variant: dedication signed "George Browne".</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: De la Marteliere, his argument against the Iesuits.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  France --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Université de Paris --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARGVMENT of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> PETER de la MARTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIERE <hi>Aduocate in the Chart of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> made, in Parliament, <hi>the Chambers thereof being</hi> aſſembled.</p>
            <p>FOR THE RECTOR AND VNIVERSITIE of <hi>Paris,</hi> Defendants and Opponents, againſt the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> Demandants, and requiring the approbation of the Letters Patents which they had obtained, giuing them power to reade and to teach publikely in the aforeſaid Vniuerſitie.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the French Copie ſet forth by publike Authoritie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Jmprinted at <hi>London,</hi> and are to be ſold neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Gate. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sir THOMAS FLEMMING <hi>Knight, Lord Chiefe Iuſtice</hi> of England</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The ſame reaſon which firſt incited mee to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this taske, hath beene a principall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue likewiſe, embolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning me to offer it vnto your Lordſhips view, and to preſume to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this diſcourſe, vnder the protection of your Lordſhips name. The matter heerein handled is a notable &amp; famous controuerſie, ariſing between the ancient and renowned Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the new and infamous, yet cunning and powerfull ſect of the Ieſuits, referred vnto the determination of Law &amp; Iuſtice, and vpon the pleadings formal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and iudicially argued and diſcuſſed: the Actor a man of Law, a learned and famous Aduocate, as this his elaborate Argument doth ſufficiently te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie; and by a learned Doctor and Rector of the
<pb facs="tcp:8637:3"/>Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſtiled <hi>os Themidis, fori deliciae.</hi> The perſons and place, before whom, and where it was repreſented; the Preſidents and Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, in that great Court Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> the ſterne and guide of the Common-wealth and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of <hi>France,</hi> the iuſtice and authority whereof amidſt the cruell rage and tempeſts of ciuill wars, as a firme anchor vpheld and preſerued the ſame, from moſt apparent ſhipwracke. As then it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be accounted, I truſt, ſuperfluous and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent in me, whoſe ſtudie is conuerſant in the Lawes of this Kingdom, to intermeddle with that which is within the compaſſe of my profeſſion, and to ioine the view of the Lawes &amp; cuſtomes of other Nations, and their manner of proceeding with thoſe of our owne, ſince that all humane Lawes haue but one ſoule, which is reaſon; &amp; one onlie function, which is the peace and quiet of Eſtates and Common-wealths: So I hope it will not be deemed preſumption or raſhneſſe, in that I preſent it vnto your Lordſhip, who worthily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideth in a ſupreme Court of Iuſtice, not inferiour vnto that of <hi>Paris,</hi> in regard either of antiquity or Maieſtie, the <hi>Baſis</hi> and pillar of this great Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, the firme ſupporter of the roiall Crowne and dignity. To you (my Lord) who in regard of the place, to which your worth, learning, piety, &amp; eminent virtues haue iuſtly aduanced you, do bear that honorable ſtile of <hi>Lord Chiefe Iuſtice;</hi> a moſt ſignificant title, denoting the ſpeciall charge and intereſt wich is committed vnto your Lorſhip in the execution of Iuſtice, which you moſt ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:3"/>wiſely, and religiouſly, doe exerciſe, with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity &amp; moderation: to you who by reaſon here of, are of the Law and profeſſors thereof <hi>Deus tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telaris,</hi> a Patron and Protector; and therefore what our induſtry can effect, is but a ſmal acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; retribution, of duty to be offered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated vnto you. Beſides, the ſubiect of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is chiefely againſt that new exceſſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie, and King-daring doctrine of the Ieſuites; which like a contagious diſeaſe, hath infected all the quarters of <hi>Europe,</hi> bred ſtrange combuſtions in Eſtates, and bene the cauſe of moſt deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; againſt the venimous poiſon whereof, there is not a more forcible preſeruatiue, then the ſeuerity of your Iuſtice; nor hath there bene euer any ſtronger bulwarke &amp; defence of the ſacred au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; perſons of our Kings, in all times and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, then the common Lawes of this Land, &amp; Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Realme, of the which your Lordſhip is the Chiefe-gardian, and by due execution doe addelife &amp; ſoule vnto them. Theſe reaſons (my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lord) haue moued me, though with the diſcouery of mine owne imperfections, to hazard theſe firſt &amp; vntimely fruites of my idle houres on your Lordſhips fauourable acceptance; wherein I ſhall haue receiued full content, my deſire &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, beeing only to yeeld vnto your Lordſhip, an humble acknowledgement of that reuerent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and due reſpect I owe vnto you, and to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips</hi> in all dutie deuoted,
<hi>GEORGE BROWNE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8637:4"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISMENT to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EADER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>To the end that thou fall not into this diſcourſe abruptly, I haue thought it not impertinent, by way of Preamble, to inſert this ſhort aduertiſment, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt inſtitution of the Ieſuites, with their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and proceedings in France, and the occaſion of this preſent controuerſie; which may ſerue, not only for an introduction, into the diſcourſe enſuing; but alſo for an explanation of ſundry paſſages, alleged therein.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer is here rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken partly out of</hi> Steeuen Paſ quier <hi>ſometime Atturney ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the King at</hi> Paris, <hi>in his 4 booke of Epiſtles &amp; laſt epiſtle, which I wold not conceale, the reſt I haue collected out of the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of</hi> France.</note> As for the Vniuerſity of Paris, I ſhall neede to ſay little, for it is ſufficiently ſet foorth in the diſcourſe, but that it was firſt founded by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, in the yeere of our Lord <hi>791.</hi> and that the Sorbonne ſo often mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is nought elſe, but a famous Colledge of Diuines, founded about the yeere <hi>1253.</hi> by <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>9.</hi> called Saint <hi>Lewis,</hi> as my Author ſaith; or as others write, by <hi>Robert</hi> brother of the ſaid King. Now as concerning the Ieſuits: this Order firſt aroſe in Chriſtendome, about the yeere <hi>1540.</hi> the Author and Founder therof, was one <hi>Ignacius Loyola</hi> a gentleman of Nauarre, who all his life time had followed the wars, and being hurt in the Towne of Pampelona, which is the chiefe City of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:5"/>whileſt his wounds were a healing, he fell to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the liues of the Fathers, reſoluing vpon the pattern of their liues to frame the tenor of his owne: afterward ioining with ſome others, who were ſome <hi>10</hi> in number, they altogether ſwore a kind of Societie; and <hi>Ignatius</hi> beeing cured they made voiages to Paris, Rome, and to Ieruſalem, and at laſt retired themſelues into Venice, where they made their aboad ſome few yeeres, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had many followers, remooued thence to Rome, where they began to make publike profeſsion of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, promiſing two things eſpecially; the one, that their principall end and ſcope, was to preach the Goſpell to the Pagans and Infidels, for to conuert them to the Chriſtian Faith: the other, freely and without reward to inſtruct Chriſtians in good letters: and for to fit and accommodate their name to their deuotion, they termed themſelues religious men of the Society of the name of Ieſus. They preſented themſelues vnto Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> of the houſe of the <hi>Farneſes,</hi> about the yeere <hi>1540.</hi> which was the time that Germany began to take armes, by reaſon of the alteration of religion; and becauſe that one of the principall points which the Germans contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, was concerning the power of the Pope, whom <hi>Martin Luther</hi> ſought to quell and pull downe: theſe making a contrary profeſsion, gaue the Pope to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the firſt and principall Vowe which they made, was to acknowledge him to bee aboue all earthly powers; yea aboue the generall and vniuerſall Councell of the Church. The Pope who at firſt doubted, whether hee ſhould approoue of them or no, and afterward had permitted them, to vſe the title of religious men, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on condition that they ſhould not bee aboue <hi>60.</hi> in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:5"/>at this promiſe began to hearken vnto them, and to giue their deuotion free paſſage: and after him <hi>Iulius</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> vntill that Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> called the <hi>Theatin,</hi> who was one of the chiefe promoters of this Order, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized them abſolutely; and conſequently, almoſt all the ſucceeding Popes, in reſpect of the ſeruices they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from them, haue endowed them with moſt large and ample priuiledges. Their Order is compoſed of two ſorts, whereof the one is called of the greater Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, the other of the leſſe. The firſt are bound vnto foure Vowes; Chaſtitie, Pouerty, and Obedience, which are the three ordinary Vowes of religious men, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they adde a fourth Vow, which is of particular o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto the Pope, as hath beene already ſaid. The ſecond are tied only to two Vowes: the one regardeth the fidelity which they promiſe to the Pope; the other is of obedience vnto the Generall of their Order. Theſe are termed lay brethren, who doe not vow Pouerty, but may hold Benefices or Offices; they may inherite their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, mothers, and kindred, enioy lands and poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and marry at a need, as if they were bound by no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Vow. They haue beſides many ſchollers, whom they cal Nouices who are (as it were) Probationers, from whence they take freſh ſupplies, and thence it is, that their Colledges are commonly called Seminaries, they hauing two ſorts of lodgings ioining together, the one for their Prieſts, the other for their ſchollers and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices. And this may ſhortly ſuffice for the deſcription of their Order.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning their proceedings in France, it ſo fell out (they beeing eſtabliſhed, as hath beene already ſet downe) that the Biſhop of Clermont tooke a liking of
<pb facs="tcp:8637:6"/>them, and was very deſirous to ſettle this Order in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris;</hi> whereupon he brought in <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi> of them, who vſed likewiſe the recommendation of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> At their firſt comming they were lodged meanly in a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Colledge of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> &amp; afterward ſet vp their abode in the Biſhop of <hi>Chemo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> his Pallace, by the permiſsion of him who firſt entertained them. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their affaires ſucceeding according to their minde, they preſented themſelues diuers times to the Court of Parlaiment, requeſting it to authorize their Order. But the king his Solliciter general, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was called Mouncieur <hi>Brulart,</hi> oppoſed himſelfe againſt all their requeſts, not for that he fauoured not the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man religion as much as any one could doe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee miſdoubted and feared aboue all things no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelties as the mothers of many errors, eſpecially in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Wherfore he told them, that if they had their minds wholyaltenated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world, they might ſafely without bringing in any new Order, confine themſelues vnder ſome one of the auncient religions approued by many Councels, or vnder ſome one of the foure Mendicants. Thus they were reiected by the Court of parliament, who not being ſatisfied with her owne opinion, nor wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to relie only thereupon, had recourſe vnto the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Theologie, by the decree whereof they were ſcenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, partly in that entitling themſelues by the name of religious men, they did neither we are the habit, neither did confine themſelues within their Cloiſters, as others did; and partly in that ſome of their opinions derogated from the liberties of the French Church. This is that decree of the yeare. <hi>1554.</hi> often mentioned in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcourſe, not long after the Biſhop of <hi>Clermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, who by his teſtament bequeathed great ſums vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:8637:6"/>them, they hauing receiued this legacie, the troubles about religion happened, in the beginning whereof there was an aſſembly of the French Church at <hi>Poiſſy</hi> in the yeare. <hi>1563.</hi> they then began to breake off their long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and preſented a requeſt vnto the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be receiued and approued not as religious men, yet at the leaſt as a College of ſchollers only. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conceiuing that this concerned principally the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors of the Church, referred them ouer vnto the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> where the Cardinal of <hi>Tournon</hi> was Preſident, as the moſt auncient Prelate, who in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tournon</hi> had before founded a company of them. By his interceſſion, they obtained to be receiued onely as a ſocietie and Colledge, vpon condition, that they ſhould be bound to take another title then that of Ieſuites, and to conforme themſelues in all, and throughal, to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church without enterpriſing any thing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ordinaries, &amp; that they ſhould firſt and formoſt renounce expreſly, and in preciſe termes, the priuileges, which their buls did import; otherwiſe if they failed herein, or obtained any other, that their approbation ſhould be vtterly void. This decree was ratified by the Court of Parliament, according to the forme and tenor thereof. Shortly vpon this they purchaſed them a houſe in the Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> and called it the Colledge of <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> in memorie of their benefactor, &amp; by reaſon that they had at that time diuers learned perſonages amongſt them, they were fauourably entertained, and drew an infinite number of ſchollers after them. And ſeeing they had the wind at will, they preſented a requeſt to the Rector &amp; Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> to be incorporated ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into. Whereupon there was a ſolemne Congregation
<pb facs="tcp:8637:7"/>aſſembled, in the which it was concluded, that before they proceeded any further, they ſhould declare whether they tooke vpon them the quality of regulars or ſeculars which did put them into a great perplexitie, for if they ſhould deny they were religious men, they belied their Vow, and to ſay they were ſo, had beene to contradict that which was enioyned them at Poiſſy, and for that they tooke no preciſe qua itie vpon them, the Vniuerſitie gaue them the repulſe. Yet would they not giue ouer but had recourſe vnto the Court of Parliament, to the end that they might gaine vpon the Vniuerſity by conſtraint that which they could not obtaine of freewill, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſhort day was giuen to both parties for to pleade, and the matter was argued on both ſides, by <hi>Paſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> for the Vniuerſitie, and <hi>Verſoris</hi> for the Ieſuits with ſuch veh mencie, as ſo great a cauſe required, &amp; in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion it was or deined that they ſhould remaine in that eſtate they were, without decreeing ought in fauor of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partie, for neither were the Ieſuits incorporated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Vniuer ſitie, as they deſired, neither were they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reading lectures as they had done in former times, as the Vniuerſitie requeſted. In this eſtate they continued vntill the yeare <hi>1594.</hi> when vpon occaſion of the execrable attempt of <hi>Peter Barrierre</hi> (who had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to murder the king <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, but was diſcouered by a Iacobin a Florentine, to whom he had reuealed it by way of confeſſion, and thereupon was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at Melum where the king was watching his opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, and found ſeaſed with a double edged knife for the purpoſe, &amp; afterward was executed for it at Paris) the Vniuerſitie renewed her auncient proceſſe againſt them, demanding to haue them baniſhed and rooted out,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:7"/>in as much as <hi>Barrier</hi> had vndertaken it by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their miſchieuous doctrine, and by the ſpeciall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of <hi>Varad</hi> rector of their colledge: &amp; the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was handled in Parlement by <hi>Arnaud</hi> who argued againſt them, and <hi>Verſoris</hi> for them, both graue and bearned aduocates: but they were ſo ſtrongly ſupported, by ſome great men, as namely the Cardinall of Bourbon and the Duke of Neuers, that at that time nothing was done againſt them, vntill that the prodigious and bold fact of <hi>Iohn Chaſtel</hi> a nouice of their ſocietie (who in the kings owne cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber at the Louure, and in preſence of his Nobles and gentlemen, ſtabbed at the king, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his belly as hee had purpoſed, by reaſon that the king ſtooped to receiue two Noble men, who kiſſed his knee, ſtrooke him in the mouth) and brake out one of his vpper teeth extorted that famous decree of the <hi>29.</hi> of december <hi>1595.</hi> whereby beſides the condemnation of <hi>Iohn Chaſtel,</hi> the Ieſuites whoſe doctrine had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him were baniſhed out of France, as enemies of the king and the eſtate, corrupters of youth, and pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the publike peace and quiet, and the houſe where the father of that monſter dwelt, which was ſituate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the gate of the Pallace being raſed, a Pyramide was erected containing (for a perpetuall monument) the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſaid decree. Thus they ſtood baniſhed vntill that as well by the inceſſant importunitie of ſome great ones about the king, as eſpecially by the earneſt interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, they were reuoked in the yeare. <hi>1604.</hi> in the moneth of Ianuarie, and the Pyramide taken away, notwithſtanding the great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and admonitions of the Court of Parlement to the contrary: yet with diuers reſtraints and conditions,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:8"/>amongſt the which one was, that they ſhould erect no College, nor make any reſidence but in the towns named in the letters of their reeſtabliſhment, without expreſſe permiſſion of the King, and particularly within the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort and iuriſdiction of the Parliament houſe of <hi>Paris,</hi> vnleſſe it were in the townes of <hi>Lyon,</hi> and <hi>La Fleche.</hi> Notwithſtanding the late King by the meanes of father <hi>Cotton,</hi> whom he had made his Confeſſor, gaue them permiſſion to returne to Paris, and made them reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all their goods, and of their Colledge of Clermont, but did not permit them to keep publike ſchoole, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with ought which concerned the Vniuerſitie: notwithſtanding that they laboured by all meanes poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be incorporated thereinto. Inſtantly vpon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtrous death of the King, they thinking it to be beſt fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in troubled water, renewed their purſuite, &amp; by the fauour of the Queene Regent, obtained the letters here mentioned, licenſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reade lecture, to ſet ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſchooles in the Vniuerſitie, whereupon the Vniuerſitie preſented a Petition vnto the Queene Regent for to preuent them therof. The Ieſuites on the contrary preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their letters, and preſented them vnto the Court of Parliament, requiring the allowance of them: the Court would not proceed without ſignifying it vnto the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, who formally oppoſed them, and thereupon it was ordered, that both parties ſhould be heard iudicial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the cauſe was remitted to the opening of the Court, the morrow vpon Saint Martins day, and from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it was put off vntil the ſeuenteenth of December; all which time it was openly and ſolemnely argued on the ſeuenteenth and ninteenth of the ſaid moneth, when <hi>Montholon</hi> the aduocate of the Ieſuites, hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb facs="tcp:8637:8"/>the allowance of the foreſaid letters, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued for them. <hi>De la Marteliere</hi> for the Vniuerſitie made this argument enſuing, whereupon followed that ſentence <hi>interlocutorie</hi> annexed vnto the end hereof. Since which time I doe not vnderſtand of any further proceeding: it is likely that the Ieſuites perceiuing the inclination of the Court, and of all in general, contrarie vnto them, and fearing to be drawne further into que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, haue retired themſelues, expecting ſome fitter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie for the effecting of their deſignes, which it is probable, that they now failing in, will hardly be able e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to bring to paſſe. This is ſhortly the whole proceſſe of this buſineſſe and controuerſie.</p>
            <p>Now I am not ignorant that diuers diſcourſes haue beene of late ſet forth in this kinde, but I dare confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently affirme, that none is of equall weight with this, in that it is no particular calumnie, but a publique account iuſtified in open Court, and publiſhed by authoritie, the Poſitions herein alleaged are theſe of the famous Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp; the ſchoole of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> (whoſe mouth this Aduocate was, &amp; ſpake as hee was inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) and not any priuate cenſure or opinion. If ought be ſaid herein which is not altogether conſonant to the doctrine of our Church (as I am certaine there is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little) let it be remembred whoſe words they are, and where they were ſpoken. Thus hoping that this may helpe to diſſipate and purge that noiſome and peſtilent aire of the Ieſuits, wherewith they ſeeke to intoxicate and infect the weake and tender conſciences of men, to the diſhonour of God and of religion, to the danger and preiudice of ſoueraigne Princes, their perſons and eſtates, to the ruine &amp; ouerthrow of their owne fortu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es,
<pb facs="tcp:8637:9"/>the ſhipwracke of all good conſcience, and ſcandall of Chriſtians, it being impoſſible that a good Chriſtian ſhould bee other then a true and loyall ſubiect to his Prince: I wil no longer withhold thee from the diſcourſe it ſelfe, praying thee fauorably to interpret my indeuors and good intention herein.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata ſic corrige.</head>
            <p>pag. 10. lin. 6. there for theſe. p. 14 l. 11. Giuinier for Cuimier. p. 18. l. 28. except for without. p. 22. l. 1. remouing for remaining. ibid. l. 22. adde which. p. 29. l. 6 Graſius for Graſſins. p. 30. l. 2. Colledge for Colledges. p. 39 l. 19 hauing for haue p. 41. l. 2. which that, dele which. p. 44. l. 13. where it is for whence it is. ibid. l. 15. maintained hierarchical for maintained the hierarchical. ibid. l. 23. where Chriſt ſhould haue for where Chriſt had p. 45. l. 16. ſingulus for ſingulis. ibid. l. 21. rigour for vigour. p 47. l. 9. concordate king Frances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, for Concordat betweene &amp;c. 50. penult direct for diuert p. 54 l. 21. which for with.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8637:9"/>
            <head>After that <hi>MONTHOLON</hi> the Aduocate of the demandants, had required the allowance of the Letters which they had obtained, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the oppoſition made againſt it by the Vniuerſitie, De la MARTELIERE <hi>for the Vniuerſitie of</hi> Paris, <hi>ſaid thus:</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Hiſtorie ſheweth vs, that after the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Cannas,</hi> in which the Romans receiued the greateſt loſſe, that euer befell them; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand Citizens, the Generall of the Armie, with fourſcore notable perſons of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, beeing kild vpon the place, the reſt of their troopes either taken, or diſperſed; the Enemie victorious and triumphant, at the gates of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the name of that magnanimous Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, brought almoſt to nothing: thoſe of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua</hi> which had alwaies nouriſhed an ill wil toward
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8637:10"/>the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, forgetting all reſpect of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce due to the Empire, without any apprehenſion of the bonds and obligations, wherewith they were bound to the people of <hi>Rome;</hi> vpon the very point of ſuch an occaſion, thought to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues Lords of <hi>Italie;</hi> ſo that in ſtead of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to the neceſsities of the State of <hi>Rome;</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the ſuccour, and aid, which was required of them; they demanded to participate in the chiefeſt dignities, and that the honor of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth might bee diuided betweene them and the <hi>Romanes.</hi> After the loſſe of our great King, whoſe Perſon ought to haue beene as deare to vs, as his Monarchie: you haue ſeene the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites (inſtead of compaſsion) ſeeking to raiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by the common calamitie of <hi>France,</hi> and without giuing vs any leaſure to ſet in order the domeſticall affaires of the Eſtate, to labour with might and maine, and to looſe no time for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire eſtabliſhment of their owne authority: I doe not ſay, that they haue demanded to partake in the greateſt charges, but by meanes of the Hoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of all your children, which they haue requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to become able to diſtribute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abſolutely, and to rule at their pleaſure, as they haue already promiſed vnto themſelues.</p>
            <p>The ſequele of the Hiſtorie touching this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous people, addeth further, that at the ouerture, which was made of ſuch a propoſition, the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> was vpon the inſtant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into an extreame indignation, againſt ſuch
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8637:10"/>ingratefull perſons, which they knew well how to accompanie with a Reſolution, beſeeming their courage: I will repreſent it in the ſame termes: <hi>Indignatione orta, ſubmoueri à Curiaiuſſos eſſe, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſúmque lictorem, qui ex vrbe educereteos, atque eo die manere extra fines Romanos iuberet; The Romanes beeing mooued with indignation, commaunded them to bee conueyed out of the Senate, and ſent a Sergeant with them to bring them out of the Citie, and forbadde them from that day forward, to enter into the Territories of the people of Rome.</hi> If God had giuen our poore nation, as much pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence &amp; ſtedfaſtneſſe, as bounty, &amp; facility; &amp; that theeies of our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding were as cleare-ſighted as thoſe of the body, the example and reſolution of the wiſeſt that euer the Sunne ſaw, might haue ſerued for a direction in this occurrence; which is vnto vs of no leſſe importance. And as this ſage counſell was ſoone ſeconded with good ſucceſſe, (for the enemie diuerting his enterpriſe from againſt the ſcat of the Empire, to receiue the affections of thoſe of <hi>Capua,</hi> gaue the Romanes time to take breath, and to make their greatneſſe appeare more redoubtable, then euer) the ſame remedie would vndoubtedly haue ſecured vs from the troubles and diuiſions, which they ſowe amongſt vs; wherein the enemies of France take farre greater aſſurance, then in all their force. But (alas) beeing giuen to vnderſtand by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold harmes wee haue ſuſtained of their deſignes, both already paſt, and yet continued vnto the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8637:11"/>fourth generation, ſhall not we be touched with a liuely apprehenſion, that at this time their onely drift is, to ſee vs the laſt of French men, and neuer to liue in repoſe; that the condition, and life of our Kings, and Princes, our owne, and that of our poſteritie be no longer aſſured?</p>
            <p>This is the third time, that the Vniuerſitie of Paris eldeſt daughter of the thrice Chriſtian Kings, hath beene reduced to this neceſsitie, by the enterpriſe of the Ieſuites: neere vpon their fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt arriuing, there was nothing elſe heard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound in this place but Propheſies of their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they would confound all politicke or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and depraue the Lawes diuine and humane: what preſages were there of the deſolation of learning, and of the ruine of the greateſt, and moſt famous Vniuerſitie, which hath beene vpon the face of the earth? Although that this were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the mouth of the greateſt perſonages, whoſe memory ſhall euer bee honoured by vs, notwithſtanding it was hard to perſwade vs, that which hath prooued ſince but too too true, euen then, when the Royall dignitie was in eſtate ſo aſſured, that it ſeemed wee neuer needed to feare any mutation: and beſides, the Catholike religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, accuſtomed to propoſe nothing but amitie, faith, and inuiolable concord, made men little to miſtruſt, that it was poſsible to bring into the Church, which had flouriſhed ſo many ages, without taking aduantage of trouble, and diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this new learning, in her old age, which hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8637:11"/>done ſo much harme, and made the remedies more dangerous then the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>As it is not commonly ſeene, that propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call declarations are fruſtrated of their effect, ſo theſe predictions haue beene authorized by the euents, in ſuch wiſe, that the Ieſuites working at one and the ſame time vpon two contraries, they haue ſtirred vp that which was of ill diſpoſition in our ſtomackes, as well the cold as the hot, and for thirtie yeares continuance haue moleſted France with ſuch a furie, that we haue found by experience, but too late, that hauing made vs loſe all fidelitie, dutie, and charitie, wee were out of hope of any recouery; if hee, whom God would haue to be the Phyſitian of our griefes, had not by his balme of amitie, and reconciliation, (a moſt gentle lenitiue, and moſt profitable for our afflictions) brought backe our quiet and repoſe. The Vniuerſitie did not then faile to giue the watchword, and to aduertiſe vs what were the cauſes of theſe mutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which were by her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily and truely repreſented, and plainely and manifeſtly laid open, the ſubiect of ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, and of ſuch a continuall feuer.</p>
            <p>The Vniuerſitie of Paris, beeing more mortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iniured, thought on nothing but ſorrow, and ſought by an eternall remembrance, to immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the merit of her benefactor; there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Temple of this great Citie, which ſhee filled not with teares, with holy ſeruices, with funerall diſcourſes in his honour: the time did not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8637:12"/>to recount the warres, the trauels, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of her King, whoſe honour can neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, nor be diminiſhed: when the Ieſuites puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with hope, and courage, did raiſe this great Nouitiate in the Suburbs of Saint <hi>Germaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A new Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge now in building for their nouices.</note> for the which, deſigning out ſo large a circuit, they doe not diſſemble any longer, but plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that they will no more faile of the prey, which they haue ſo long purſued: they doe ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie, and augment their Citadels, and withall doe denounce warre againſt the Vniuerſitie, vnder the fauour of Letters, which by importunitie they had obtained in the moneth of Auguſt, in the yeare, one thouſand ſixe hundred and tenne: they require to haue the inſtruction of the youth, to haue power to ſet open their houſes, and to reade Lecture in all ſorts of Sciences, in ſtead that the yeare before, they had required permiſsion to reade onely in Diuinitie: againſt which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, the Vniuerſity then oppoſing it ſelfe, they with-drewe their Letters, fearing that in ſuch a ſeaſon, the great inconueniences of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and of their inſtitution might bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</p>
            <p>Their laſt Letters were preſented vnto the Court, the three and twentieth of the moneth of Auguſt, and (as there is no artifice whatſoeuer, of which they haue not the practiſe in hand) more then three weekes before, they had canuaſſed the faculties of the Vniuerſitie, yea they vaunted of the conſent of ſome particular men, which had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8637:12"/>alwaies thought well of them, they did publiſh their victory without any reſiſtance, they did preſſe with might and maine the approbation of their letters. The court notwithſtanding ordered, that they ſhould be communicated to the rector, and the vniuerſity, which hauing bin done, and the body thereof aſſembled, neuer any man ſaw more reſolution ſhewed in the defence of their liberty, yea with all earneſtneſſe. And there were but three, wherof the facultie of the Canon law is compoſed, which failed her at this neede, (as if the bloud, which they haue in their veines, did proceed from ſome other different nouriſhment, and that they had habituated themſelues to ſome ſtrange affection,) notwithſtanding being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to yeeld vnto the reſt which were in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number, (yea a hundred for one) the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was framed and receiued in this parliament, vnder the name of the rector of the vniuerſity in generall. The Court hauing done me this honor, to name me the aduocate of the vniuerſity, I haue bleſſed that day a hundred times, which I will hold alwaies as deere as that of my life, in which my ſmall labour, and merit haue found ſo great a recompence by your iudgement, as that I may render to my country, to whom I owe the good fortune of my birth, &amp; to the vniuerſity, to whom I am bound for my education, this witneſſe of my duety, and reſpect, and that I may be reckoned by poſterity in the number of thoſe, to whom this defence in his time hath happened.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8637:13"/>
            <q>Me quoque principibus permiſtum agnoſcat Achiuis.</q>
            <p>Our time of pleading of the Parliament paſt, ended the morrow vpon S. <hi>Martins</hi> day; our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries vaniſhed as fire in a clowd, leauing vnto the Vniuerſitie the extreame ſorrow of being fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated of ſo honourable and ſo lawfull a combat, to which ſhee had been excited by the Iuſtice of her cauſe, and by the force of neceſſity.</p>
            <q>Plorauêre ſuis non reſpondere fauorem Speratum meritis.</q>
            <p>In the time that the Vniuerſitie imagined ſhee was at ſome reſt, and that the Ieſuites did promiſe openly they would not vndertake any further, and that they would containe themſelues, wee feele and perceiue, that they oppreſſe vs, and that the cuill hatched long before hand, could not ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly be eſchewed. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, contemning the authority of the King (who would haue the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Letters to depend on your appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation) and that of the Court, (which had ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the Vniue ſitie ſhould firſt be heard vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her oppoſition) wee ſee that they are eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and vpon their owne authoritie doe inſtruct Schollers in the Colledge of <hi>Clermont,</hi> vſe all ſcholaſtical functions, and by their witty ſleights, they will make vs pay intereſt for our ſmall time of quiet, (as ſaid the prouident Bat of <hi>Athens</hi>) du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the which, we haue ſeene the weeds to grow vp, which we ſuffered to be ſowne.</p>
            <p>As the Vniuerſitie hath witneſſed againe this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8637:13"/>time to all the world: by her obedience that ſhee would haue ſlept, referring the beſt of her inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to the benefit of Tyme, ſo ſhee could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that now any one in the world can thinke it ſtrange, that ſhee would deſire not to die, and ſince that her peace within doth depend in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king warre, night and day, without, and that no other plaiſter can be applied vnto her griefe ſhee was forced to renue the inſtant purſuit of this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to ad a requeſt, for the reſtoring of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe anew: whereunto finding the Court well diſpoſed ſhee hath reaſon to promiſe vnto her ſelfe vpon the whole matter as ready a diſpatch, as happie, and fauourable.</p>
            <p>And becauſe (my Lords) that in my owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, I acknowledge my forces diſproportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to ſo heauie a burthen, yea I ingenuouſly confeſſe my ſelfe to bee the leaſt of thoſe of my profeſſion, which could worthily acquit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thereof, fauour him I beſeech you, with your benigne audience, which ſpeaketh by your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, nay rather countenance the cauſe the moſt important, which hath been pleaded in our memory in that of our anceſtours, yea of all <hi>France,</hi> the iſſue, and euent whereof will conſerue our lawes with the ſweetneſſe of our liberty, or make vs ſee our ruine without any more hope, or remedie; the which I will handle, as ſuccinctlie as I may, and with ſo much truth and mildnes, that I hope to leaue no ſubiect to accuſe ought but the euill wils, and ſubtill practiſes of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8637:14"/>againſt whom the Vniuerſity contenteth her ſelfe to oppoſe a wiſdome truly Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> hath bin from all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended for her ſingular deuotion, &amp; erudition, by meanes whereof many hereſies, and thoſe of people farre remote haue beene conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced: the Doctors thereof haue ſo inſiſted in the waies of the holy ſpirit in the Catholike Church, that by reaſon of the reputation of this ſincerty, there haue beene heretikes, which haue agreed to take them for Iudges, and according to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, haue paſſed condemnation vpon their errors according to the example of the Donatiſts of <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frica,</hi> who although they were proud, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, yet in the cauſe which concerned one <hi>Caecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus,</hi> in the requeſt which they preſented to the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> they demanded that the Iudges which ſhould be giuen them, might bee <hi>Gaules,</hi> and it hath beene written to her honor by <hi>Vern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rus</hi> in <hi>faſciculo temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that learning leauing <hi>Greece,</hi> was come to <hi>Rome,</hi> and thence to make her aboad at <hi>Paris,</hi> vnder the protection of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, who founded the ſame ſeuen hundred yeeres agoe, and that the light of learning being for certain ages extinguiſhed, was again lightened in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris;</hi> the Popes <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> the third in their decretall Epiſties, haue left for a perpetuall bleſſing vnto this Vniuerſity that ſhe had peopled the moſt part of the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks of Chriſtendome. And before them <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> the third, taking notice of the error of <hi>Gilbert
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8637:14"/>Porretan,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Poictiers,</hi> would not decree any thing therein, without the aduiſe of the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> by reaſon of the multitude of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, wherewith it was repleniſhed, ſaith <hi>Otho Friſingenſis,</hi> an Hiſtorian of merit, and indeed the Biſhop was ouercome by the diſputations of M. <hi>Adam de petit Pont,</hi> a famous doctor of our Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity.</p>
            <p>Let vs adde conſequently vnto this recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that of the Popes <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the fift, &amp; <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſixth, who haue ſaid that <hi>Paris</hi> was as the neuer dried ſource, whence the riuer of ſcience did flow, which watered continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Church of God, and the inſtruction of all Chriſtendome. And it is fiue hundred yeeres agoe, that the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> might boaſt of this high ſtile of honor, which aduanceth her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the Schooles in the world, <hi>Studium Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſe fundamentum eccleſiae.</hi> What more honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſtimony can there bee, then that which is read in the Regiſters of the Vniuerſity, that in the yeere three hundred, ſeuenty eight, the Church being afflicted with a great Schiſme, the ſacred Colledge of Cardinals, <hi>Apoſtolica ſede va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante,</hi> did ſolemnlie inuite the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> to contribute to the good of the Church, for to defend her from intruſion.</p>
            <p>In the yeere foure hundred, and ten, another <hi>Schiſme</hi> hauing giuen occaſion of aſſembling the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the Doctors of the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> and amongſt others M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Gerſon,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:8637:15"/>which was Chancellor thereof, named the thrice Chriſtian doctor, in honour of the thrice Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, which had ſent him, by their learning made knowne that the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> was the mother, and Nurſe of all good, and holy inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, that ſhee had conſerued the puritie of Theologie, mainteined the Epiſcopall dignitie, had alwaies oppoſed her ſelfe againſt ſtrange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, nouelties, and ſuperſtitions. Which hath made men to conceiue ſo reuerent an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> that from all the quarters of <hi>Europe,</hi> yea from the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, her aduiſe, and reſolutions haue been ſought for, and preferred to that of other Schooles. To conclude, be it ſpoken to the praiſe of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> hath made the Church of <hi>France</hi> to floriſh aboue all parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches of the world; in token whereof the Popes, <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixth, and <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond would ſolemnly giue notice of their elections vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the laſt of theſe two witneſſed, that at the purſuite, and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> he was moued to defend the Councell of <hi>Baſil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So may we ſay, that the tree of this doctrine planted ſo long ſince, hath produced ſo good fruit, that there is not any one, which hath fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented ſtrange nations, who will not ſay, but that the deuotion of <hi>France,</hi> and principallie of the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſurpaſſeth that of all other peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which it may bee is more in outward ſhew,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8637:15"/>but as different from that of ours, as the ſhadow from the ſubſtance. As the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> hath been religiouſly deuoute, ſo hath ſhee neuer wanted the reſpect, and obedience towards our Kings her protectors, and withall, her power hath conſerued the royall rights againſt all vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Our hiſtories doe iuſtifie, that the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity hath alwaies couragiouſly oppoſed her ſelfe againſt all attempts vpon the power of Kings, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the abuſes, which are committed contrary to the holy decrees, and conſtitutions of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, hath held great authority in the aſſemblies of the Gallicane Church, for to maintaine the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſame, witneſſe the appeale brought by the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> and maintained in this Court, againſt Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the cleuenth, who would haue leuyed tenths vpon the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> whence occaſion was taken in a diffama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory libell, which was then publiſhed againſt the King, and the Clergy of his Realme, to quarrell particularly with the Vniuerſity, which appeale, the Vniuerſity did reiterate in the time of <hi>Lewes</hi> the eleuenth, from the buls decreed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices electiue. Vpon this ſubiect, we ſee ſo many oppoſitions framed by the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the power, and faculties of the <hi>Legats</hi> ſent into <hi>France,</hi> as againſt that of the Cardinall of S. <hi>Peter, ad vincula,</hi> and of Cardinall <hi>Ballue,</hi> wherein the Vniuerſity did ſummon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sollicitor</hi> generall named then <hi>de ſaint Romain</hi> to aſſiſt her, which made an ancient French author to write that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8637:16"/>Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> was the key of Chriſtendome, the moſt carefull promotreſſe of the rights of the Gallicane Church.</p>
            <p>Alſo our Kings haue eſpecially cheriſhed her, for it is read, that ſhee accompanied the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning in triumph from the battaile of <hi>Bouines,</hi> and it is a thing remarkeable, that King <hi>Philip</hi> the Long, hauing aſſembled the eſtates of his Realme and the Vniuerſity, all others did ſweare fidelity vnto the King, as ſoueraigne, onely the Vniuerſity did not ſweare at all, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Giuinner</hi> hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the preface to the Pragmaticke ſanction, becauſe that by her inſtruction, we learne to breath with the aire of <hi>France,</hi> fidelity towards our Prince, and loue to our Countrey: and who knoweth not the praiſe which the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> bare away from the mouth of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond, hauing vnderſtood by the Cardinall <hi>Beſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion,</hi> that ſhee had hindered her ſchollers, from being inrolled in the troopes of thoſe,
<note place="margin">This was in the time of <hi>Char'es</hi> the 7.</note> who made the publique weale a pretext of their rebellion. Vpon this conſideration <hi>Dumeſnil</hi> the King his At<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urney generall, whoſe memorie can neuer die, ſaid that the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> was receiued to pleade in this Court, not only in her particular cauſes concerning her priuiledges, but alſo in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which concerne the publique eſtate of this Realme.</p>
            <p>The Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> is compoſed of foure facuities, the firſt is of Diumity, which beareth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the prize and hath the aduantage aboue all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8637:16"/>the reſt: this is that ſcience, which treateth of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall things, which lifteth a man vp in ſpirit vnto the heauens, which teacheth the ſaluation of mankind, the reunion of the creature to his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. To the ſtudy of the faculty of Theologie of <hi>Paris,</hi> is attributed the perfect, and diuine inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſchoole diuinity, held in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church to be the infallible rule, whereby to iudge of the myſteries of faith, and of religion, the ſubiect for which the learning of this ſchoole is ſo much admired.</p>
            <p>The ſecond faculty is of thoſe, who handle the knowledge of the Lawes, who are to teach that, which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, is the moſt diuine thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, that is, to giue good counſell in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and directions in pollicies. The third is of Phiſitians which haue care of the health of the body: the laſt of the Arts, which laieth open the treaſures of humane learning, of the tongues, and of Philoſophy. If that our diuinity hath had the honor for puritie, the knowledge of the law of not being equalled, our Phiſicke to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all others; the laſt which is as the ſeed, and nurſery of the former, hath the teſtimonie of the moſt eloquent <hi>Italians</hi> of our age, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that they haue learned of the Maſters of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> the purity of the Latine, and of the other tongues, which yet at this day are not to be found any other where ſo perfect. Now as the eſtate of the Church Vniuerſall is ſecular,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8637:17"/>ſo the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> is ſecular, the Rector, the Chancellour, the Deane, the Syndickes, the Cenſors of the foure faculties, the <hi>Proctors</hi> of the foure Nations, the Deputies, Maſters, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors are ſecular; the Regulars, as are the Ieſuits, were neuer admitted there into, but by grace and by adoption, vnder a double condition, the one to be perpetually excluded from all offices and dignities, without being able to participate in them, the other not to keep publique ſchooles, but ſimply and in particular to inſtruct thoſe of their order, as it is contained in the firſt addition of the Capitularies of <hi>Charles</hi> the great. Chap. 47. <hi>Vt ſcholae in Monaſterio non habeantur niſi eorum qui oblati ſunt; That in Monaſteries no Schooles ſhould be kept but onely for thoſe who were profeſſed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the prime and ſupreame lawes of the policie of the Vniuerſity who is ſubiect to the pollitique, and eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrate, that is to ſay, to the Lawes, and equity of the Eſtate, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth reformations from the royall ordinances, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the times, and ſeaſons, motions and neceſſities of the Realme: when on the contrarie the Regulars doe depend and tie themſelues to the rule of their order, which they receiue from their ſuperiors, being religious men, as they are, whom they are bound by their vow to obey, and the Ieſuits aboue all others, ſince that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in all things their generall, as Ieſus Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>erth: they are ſo far off from receiuing reformation, in their maners, their rule, or policy,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8637:17"/>from the Magiſtrate or Biſhops, that they do not in any ſort acknowledge them, &amp; from whoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer they hold themſelues to bee wholy exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted.</p>
            <p>This was the reaſon wherefore in times paſt the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> oppoſed her ſelfe againſt the like enterprize of the <hi>Iacobins,</hi> which would haue kept publique ſchoole, and boaſted of their great learning, and notable ſeruices, which their Order had done the Catholike Church; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the chiefeſt men, which then were of the Church, hauing no preiudicate opinion by reaſon of any particular Intereſt, or deſigne, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the confuſion of two bodies altogether ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, did cauſe theſe religious Regulars to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from their purſuit, and the Magiſtrates which feared leaſt the Vniuerſity ſhould be tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into a Regular eſtate, did hinder them from being receiued. And indeed, what deſigne can be more ordinary vnto religious men accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the greateſt ſimplicity and modeſty, then by their example, and inſtruction to draw men vnto the perfection of their rule, to make them religious men and Monkes, as they are, ſo that by little and little we ſhould haue ſeene the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall Order of the Church to become ſubiect, and depend of a Regular Order, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth depriued and deſtitute of her Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, herſcruice abandoned, the charges of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate forſaken, or furniſhed with thoſe, who, after their choice, by reaſon of their order, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would haue beene found to be leaſt capable.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8637:18"/>
            <p>And in regard hereof Cardinall <hi>Borromeus,</hi> whoſe memory is alwaies to be reuerenced, tooke away the gouernment of the Colledges which he had eſtabliſhed in the Archbiſhopricke of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> from thoſe of the ſociety of the Ieſuites, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Church had more need of Paſtors, then of religious men. In <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe, they could neuer get licence to keepe publique ſchoole, or reade to anie other, then to thoſe of their owne houſe in the Vniuerſity of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> or in that of <hi>Alcala de Henares,</hi> which are the two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Vniuerſities of the Country, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hauing attempted it vpon an occaſion, which was euidently fauourable vnto them, they were not admitted. In the yeere 1563. King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> being to eſtabliſh a Seminary at <hi>Salamanca;</hi> for the ſtudie of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mſh,</hi> who reſorted vnto him for ſuccour, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites ſought to haue the gouernment thereof, and had prouiſion, and permiſſion accordingly, as well by reaſon of the knowledge, which they had of the tongue, and of the manners of thoſe who were to be inſtructed; as for ſome other grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enterprize then intended, and alſo by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation of the Duke of <hi>Medina Cidonia,</hi> whoſe mediation they vſed; notwithſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the oppoſition of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> they were put from their purpoſe, except that the ſeruice, which <hi>Spaine</hi> receiueth of the Ieſuites was able to vanquiſh the protection due vnto the lawes, and to the policy of this Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8637:18"/>and the complaint of the Engliſhmen is not ſecret; that the Ieſuits hauing the guiding of the Seminaries eſtabliſhed in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> by the fauour they haue, doe allure, and violently draw vnto them the beſt wits of their nation; and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time that they beſieged our Vniuerſity, haue not wee felt the ſame loſſes, greeuous to moſt of the great families of this Kingdome, and preiudiciall to the Eſtate.</p>
            <p>It is well knowne to euery one, that the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its comming into <hi>France,</hi> vnder the recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth, who was of the houſe of the <hi>Caraffaes,</hi> could not be receiued, nor approued of by the Church of <hi>France,</hi> as they are not yet at this day, and from that time they haue had all the Clergy in maine oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. In the yeere 1563. they addreſſed themſelues to the aſſembly made at <hi>Poiſsi,</hi> vnder the raigne of King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, after that they had begged the fauour of the Cardinals of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and of <hi>Tournon,</hi> perſonages of great power, as they neuer faile cunningly to curry fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with thoſe who are in credit, and authoritie, and diſſembling the quality, and degrees of their Vow, did hide the ſecret of their rule, ſo that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing prayed to be receiued as ſimple ſchollers, it was yeelded vnto them, by the Act of that aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, allowed of in this Court, which is the one, and only title of their introduction into <hi>France.</hi> It was then thought that much was done, and that the inconueniences of this noueltie, were ſurelie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8637:19"/>prouided for, by impoſing vpon them Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of altering their name, &amp; their title of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues abſolutely, as other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons, to the Iuriſdiction and controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Biſhops, preciſely to bee bound, that they ſhould firſt and formoſt expreſly renounce the priuiledges mentioned by their buls, without ſeeking to obtaine anie others vpon paine of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the grace and fauour which had beene gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them.</p>
            <p>But this ſerued not to any other end, but to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie their reſolution, and to giue them hope of that which remained, for without any other war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or authority, they eſtabliſhed themſelues in the Vniuerſitie, contrary to the oppoſition plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt them, referred vnto Counſell, and not yet decided, and ſo remained vntill the edict, and decree of the yeere, 1595. by which they were driuen and baniſhed out of the Kingdome. By the letters of reeſtabliſhment, which they haue obtained, and which haue beene verified in this Court in the beginning of the yeere ſix hundred, and foure, it is contained amongſt other things, that they ſhall not haue power to erect any Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor to make any reſidence in any other Towne or part of the Realme, but there, where they were then eſtabliſhed by appointment of their letters, without expreſſe permiſſion of the King: and particularly within the iuriſdiction of this Parliament, except onely in the Townes of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and <hi>Fleche,</hi> which they being not willing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8637:19"/>preſently to thwarte, nor openly to band them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> whom they knew to bee in the particular protection of this great parliament, whoſe Iuſtice the brighter it ſhineth, the leſſe they dare behold it, they haue circumuented the accuſtomed weakeneſſe and folly of the ſimple people, vpon which foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they build their moſt firme deſſignes, and by the eſtabliſhment of one or two and forty Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which they haue in the Townes of this Realme, in ſtead of twelue or foureteene, which they had in former times, haue imagined, that cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off, and diuerting the ſtreames, which runne into this great riuer, they would wholy dry it vp. And there is no doubt, but that the Vniuerſity hath thereby felt a great impayring; and that they had conceiued ſuch an opinion of the ſucceſſe, that they already gaue out that men tooke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their worth, and that they were eſteemed neceſſary, that the Vniuerſity ſought them, and offered them the Colledges of <hi>Pleſsis du Mans,</hi> and of <hi>Cholets</hi> to ioyne them to that of <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> they reported vnder hand, that the City of <hi>Paris</hi> ſhould come to that paſſe at length, that it ſhould giue them the Colledge of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> or that any other ſhould be built them as large as that. But God would that the ſmoke of theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentations ſhould doe no hurt, but to the eyes of the Ieſuites, and that the fruit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of their reuenge hath fallen out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then they expected; for they confeſſe, that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8637:20"/>the Vniuerſity remaining as it doth without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, or receiuing them into it, their other Colledges cannot long continue, and that their deſignes for the inſtruction of youth, wilbe well nigh fruitleſſe, and to no purpoſe, whereunto in as much as they are ſtirred vp with the deſire of rule, and by the conſideration of that greatneſſe, to which they aſpire, not being able to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by the force of the lawes of our Vniuerſity, by the authority of your decrees, nor the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their reeſtabliſhment, we are conſtrained to diſcouer one of the myſteries of their ambition.</p>
            <p>Although that the Ieſuits greatly wronging learning, doe mangle, and diuerſifie the ancient authors, that they are altogether ignorant in the ſecret of the tongues, yea that in the Colledges, where they account themſelues ſetled, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to continue, as in <hi>Italy,</hi> and in <hi>Sauoy,</hi> they do altogether contemne them, and reade no other books, but ſuch as are compoſed by thoſe of their own ſociety; notwithſtäding the reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is highly eſteemd, the which they can neuer vſurpe nor adde vnto their trophies, as long as the Vniuerſity continueth without Ieſuites. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus Marcellinus</hi> writeth, that it was ſufficient for the Phyſitians of his time, in recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their knowledge, to haue ſtudied in <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria;</hi> ſo it addeth vnto the merit of any man, be he neuer ſo learned, to haue ſtudied in <hi>Paris;</hi> the ſtrangers euidently ſhew it, in ſeeking the alliance of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> to grace their ſchooles,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8637:20"/>as that of <hi>Pauia,</hi> called her ſelfe, as <hi>Crantzius</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, her daughter, that of <hi>Milan</hi> her ſiſter, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth <hi>Paulus Iouius</hi> in the life of one of the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this reputation of great importance, which can giue, or take from them the choice of the beſt wits, they cannot manage the inſtruction of youth, according to their minde, any where elſe, as well as at <hi>Paris,</hi> the ſeat of the Empire, the place, where the royalty reſideth, whereon the eyes of <hi>France</hi> are ſet, the reſidence of the great &amp; ſoueraigne aſſemblies; no where out of <hi>Paris</hi> is there ſuch ciuilitie, out of <hi>Paris</hi> little experience is to be learned in affaires, elſewher, the courſe of the world is not knowne. To conclude, it is the braine of the body of this eſtate, if they cannot poſſeſſe this part, their hope is halfe fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe that imploying for the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the youth of other Cities, men of little vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which had more need to be taught, then to teach, and being conſtrained to keepe the moſt able and ſufficient they haue, to make ſhew and muſter withall, the children doe not onely not profit by them, but neither are they able to diſcharge what they haue vndertaken; ſo that the aſſurance, which they giue out of their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures failing, the Vniuerſity ſhould be repleniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſhee doth begin with ſchollers; which they retaine with all their might.</p>
            <p>Secondly inſtructing the youth out of <hi>Paris,</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8637:21"/>and moſt often the beſt wits doe leaue them, and eſcape their hand; &amp; then, when hauing gotten more knowledge, their iudgement is aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, they are diuerted by a quite contrary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction vnto theirs, ſo that their harueſt neuer commeth to perfection, for to confirme and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle their doctrine, and inſtitution, they muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies haue their eye vpon their ſcholler, whom they themſelues doe faſhion, and inure to affaires of the world, ſo that he taketh nothing in hand but by their aduiſe, direction, and order, and hee muſt yeeld them an account of what he doeth; they neuer let looſe the bridle after they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him in ſome matter, which concerneth his particular intereſt, and they haue long time had experience, that by meanes of the bringing vp of the children of thoſe of <hi>Paris,</hi> they know the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of houſes, they gouerne the hearts, and wils of thoſe, who commit vnto their truſt that which they hold moſt deare: a great augmentation of their power.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon, yet more weighty, and of greater force is this: The Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> hath at all times had the Colledge of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> in ſingular reuerence, and eſtimation, founded by our good King Saint <hi>Lewes,</hi> it honoreth her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, and the conſciences of men doe willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmit themſelues to her decrees, the French Church taketh great aſſiſtance from the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, which is ſo much the more legitimate, by how much the more it is very ancient, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8637:21"/>by tradition from our fathers vnto vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with all ſufficiencie, learning and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the Ieſuites would haue gotten an abſolute vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, if they could haue ruinated this fortreſſe of the French Church, and of our beliefe, they ſhould be without feare of euer ſeeing either their doctrine, or the bookes of their ſociety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, or controlled.</p>
            <p>It is not then ſuccour, or ayde, which the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits ſeeme to offer the Vniuerſitie, but (to ſpeake properly) they ſeeke her ouerthrow; and with what face dare they maintaine, that our doctors are defectiue and faulty? <hi>Gamaches, du Val le</hi> Clerke <hi>Yſambert Hennequin</hi> doe inſtruct ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and plainely, that by learned lectures the ſchoole of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> hath her exerciſes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually repleniſhed with fiue hundred daily Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors. For inſtruction in humane learning there are as ſufficient, as euer there were. <hi>Marſille Morel, Bourbon, Granger, Hardiuiliers,</hi> and others, the leaſt of whom hath more knowledge, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in the tongues then all the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of the Ieſuites. Alſo this is not the vtmoſt of that which they ſtriue for, they haue long ſince giuen out, that nothing is well done, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth not from them, nothing is perfect but their life, their diſcipline, and their rule: they want no ſeede of diuiſions to caſt amongſt vs, and doe laye vpon vs manifeſt aſperſions, as they began in the yeere, 1575. in calumniating the faith of the Vniuerſity touching the immaculate
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8637:22"/>conception of the holy Virgin, bearing the holy father in hand, that the only hinderance and let which kept the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> from being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in <hi>France,</hi> was in that the doctrine of the diuines of <hi>Paris,</hi> maintained the conſtitution of the Councel of <hi>Baſil.</hi> And their ordinary practiſes in places where they are eſtabliſhed, may make vs iudge ſufficientlie of their intention, in that they receiue no doctrine, nor inſtruction, but from thoſe of their owne ſociety. Maſter <hi>George Engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemnis</hi> would haue read Philoſophie at <hi>Rouen,</hi> Maſter <hi>Matthew Geliſſemius</hi> at <hi>Doway</hi> would haue profeſſed the ſame likewiſe to the Engliſh Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, but were both hindered by them: in the Towne of <hi>Auignion,</hi> there being in the Couent of the <hi>Fryars Minimes</hi> an excellent diuine which read lecture to the religious men of his order, manie moued by his learning did frequent his lectures, but they propounded and proſecuted the matter ſo earneſtly, that none elſe, beſides the religious men of their owne houſe could bee admitted. And not long ſince Maſter <hi>Claude Berthin</hi> a verie excellent ſcholler, and bacheler in diuinity being deſirous to preach at <hi>La Fleche,</hi> could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by reaſon of their oppoſition. At this day in all <hi>Germany</hi> beſides the Colledge of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> there is no reader, nor ſchoole, but either of Ieſuites, or Proteſtants: the image of thoſe perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious extremities, to which they would bring vs; and already in <hi>France</hi> we ſee Vniuerſities vtterlie ouerthrowne, Colledges of ancient foundation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8637:22"/>quite rooted out by their meanes agreeable vnto the preſage, which <hi>Monſieur de Pontac,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bazas</hi> made of them aboue forty yeers agoe, doe not they (although it be miſtruſted and ſuſpected to be falſe) make vſe of the Bull, which they ſay they haue obteined from pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth, by the which contrary to the Lawes, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Pontamouſſon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. his immediate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor, the dignity of the Rector-ſhippe is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto the Ieſuites quite excluding all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and there doe they exerciſe by this meanes a perpetuall dictatorſhip. They haue not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ancient houſes of Religion, for to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate themſelues, as at <hi>Bourges,</hi> they would haue taken vp the houſe of the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> that of the <hi>Iacobins</hi> at <hi>Orleans,</hi> in <hi>Moldania</hi> and <hi>Walachia,</hi> they haue driuen out the religious men, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated vnto themſelues their poſſeſſions, at <hi>Lucerna,</hi> they haue driuen out the Chartreux, in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> they had done the like to other Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treux, and had taken vp their ancient Monaſterie, if <hi>Don Quincana</hi> a Spaniard of that order had not preuented them, who hindred their purpoſe: neither doe they endeuour to eſtabliſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in any place in the world, but by the ruine of others.</p>
            <p>They alleadge, that they teach for nothing, and that it is a great eaſe to fathers which are of ſmall ability. Can it be poſſible, that we ſhould be yet ſeduced with ſo ill and falſe an opinion, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8637:23"/>had ſo euident knowledge, and ſo cleere proofe before our Eyes, this imagination can cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the truth? The Ieſuits haue no Colledges, which are not founded with the ſubſtance of thoſe whom they ſo teach for nothing, and thoſe of great reuenue. It is ſtrange, that being reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed but ſix yeeres agoe, they ſhould poſſeſſe more wealth in <hi>France,</hi> then in anie other part of Chriſtendome. Soe doe wee cheriſh our owne hurt, recompenſing more liberally the harme which they doe vs, then our enemies doe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, which they receiue from them. To one of their Colledges alone they haue belonging two thouſand pound a yeere rent, and a hundred thouſand Crownes beſtowed in building, they haue vnited Abbeyes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Franes fieſs</hi> are lands which none but gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth them is made no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (as they terme it) and therefore the king hath a fine for alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, and no man, who is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe them without his leaue.</note> Priories, and Benefices, and with one blow haue diſappointed, and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated the founders, Patrons and religious men, they got at one time alone foureteene thouſand Crownes, vpon the laſt ſale of the franke fees, and lands, which newly came to the Crowne, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon there was an edict made to inhibite them, (we may ſee whether we are to thanke their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty) or elſe they had gone further. Whether are theſe the religious men of rare pietie, who prayed the great Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> to imploy the liberality which he offered them, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the poore, and eaſing of his people? or thoſe dainty Courtiers, which <hi>Ammianus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus</hi> deſcribeth: Who, that it might not be obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto them, that they had ſerued for nought,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8637:23"/>or becauſe they would not be meaſured by the rule of others. <hi>Stipendia ſua manu non recipiebant, ſed expanſa chlamyde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of threeſcore and three Colledges, which are in the Vniuerſitie, there is not one, except the Colledge of the <hi>Graſsius,</hi> which hath any foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, or wages, for the Regents: the foundation of the Colledge of <hi>Nauarre</hi> hath for their wages in all but foure pounds a yeere at the moſt, there is not the leaſt ſeruant of the Ieſuits, which hath not a better remembrance. Learning is not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without the ſweetneſſe of ſome recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, our anceſtors would leaue this to mens diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, according to their meanes, and as the time required, notwithſtanding they appointed ſome reward for to ſtirre vp emulation, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſpurre of vertue, without any conſtraint at all; there was neuer poore ſcholler, whoſe excuſe hath not beene, and is receiued, and now muſt the imagination forſooth, that they will eaſe vs of ſome ſmall expences, hinder vs from diſcerning the ſhadow from the ſubſtance, make vs reiect, and contemne the true ſciences, which the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity doth preſerue by her owne proper merit, (as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Mathematicians</hi>) and expell diuine, and noblemindes, theſe wits of fine gold, for to eſtabliſh thoſe of iron and lead, and to make them ſucceed in their roomes. Let the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſity be gratified, but with the third part of an hundred thouſand Crownes a yere rent, which the Ieſuits poſſeſſe, all ſhalbe done there freely &amp;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8637:24"/>we ſhall ſee learning flouriſh more then euer it did, or rather let the foundation of the Colledge be reduced vnto that which is neceſſary, and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded according to the courſe of the time, there will be ſufficient and if we will take neuer ſo little paine, it were as eaſie to eſtabliſh the good as to know the euill, if we are not ſo vnfortunate, as that we will diſdaine our owne, for to entertaine ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>We reade in the 22. Chapter of <hi>Deuterno.</hi> that God did expreſly forbid, that a vineyard ſhould be pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of diuers kinds of plants, to mixe wool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and linnen together, to ſow a fielde with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ſeedes: The nouelty of the inſtitution of the Ieſuites ſocietie, their doctrine different from that of the Church, and from the Theologie of our ſchoole, the which neuer ſwarued, nor went out of the eclipticke line of truth, yea diameter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe and directlie oppoſite, and contrary to the authority of free Monarchies hath beene the cauſe, that our anceſtors haue earneſtly withſtood the receiuing of the Ieſuites, and that the ſchoole of <hi>Sorbone</hi> then furniſhed with the greateſt and moſt famous doctors of Chriſtendome, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part whereof were aſſiſtant at the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> made that famous decree of the yeere 1554. which conteineth a propheſie of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries which were felt ſithence, and endured pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, God for our chaſtiſment hath ratified, ſo that the ineuitable neceſsity, in which the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, and imprudent paſsions of the Ieſuites doe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8637:24"/>ingage vs, the extreme perill which they haue brought our Countrey vnto, cannot but vntie our tongue, although we ſhould haue been mute and tongue tyed, all our liues, for to performe the ſame duty againe at this preſent, guided by the light of thoſe, to whom we would take it for a ſpeciall grace to be reſembled, either for ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, or honeſty, not being able to faile vpon this occaſion to diſcharge our conſciences for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and preſeruation of the publique weale, and for the aduancement of truth, vnleſſe we will bee thought more zealous to our owne ruine, then affectionate to our ſafety.</p>
            <p>Wherein, as our intention is, to take the ſame decree of our ſchoole, for the rule and meaſure of this demonſtration, which the Ieſuites could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer procure to be cenſured at <hi>Rome,</hi> where our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion is knowne, and where it is not yet out of memory, what oppoſition was made there, as well as here at the eſtabliſhment of the Ieſuites, which had preuailed, had it not beene in regarde of their fourth vow; ſo we will begin with the ſame proteſtation which the diuines of <hi>Paris</hi> then made, in which we deſire to liue, &amp; die, and for the good of the Catholike Church, and of the holy Sea, would confirme it with our blood; that wee haue no deſire to enterpriſe any thing either in thought, word, or deed, againſt the authority of our holy fathers the Popes. But contrariwiſe all of vs in generall, and each of vs in particular, like obedient children, doe acknowledge the holie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8637:25"/>father to be the Vicar of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the vniuerſall Paſtour of the Church, to whom God hath giuen fulnes of power therein, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, and conſtitutions are to be obeyed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced, kept, and obſerued; and as the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> had neuer other beliefe, ſo now doth ſhee openlie pronounce it with her heart, and with all true affection.</p>
            <p>Our Vniuerſity together with all Chriſtian people hath reaſon to take offence, and ſcandall at the vſurpation which the Ieſuites haue made vpon the holy name of Ieſus, in attributing parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly vnto themſelues this ſpeciall, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable name, which cannot bee giuen for a marke and diſtinction amongſt Chriſtians, but is a name of effect, and of office, which apportai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto none, but to the Sauiour of the world, neuertheleſſe, as if the Ieſuites in a kinde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie or proportion, could doe ſomething in the Church like vnto that, they would make men belieue, that their ſociety is eſſentially neceſſary for the Catholique religion, that without them, it cannot ſubſiſt, they ſay that they were choſen by the diuine prouidence, for a rule, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in theſe latter times: <hi>Ad ſilentium tumidis magisterijs imponendum, defectus aliorum corrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos &amp; ſupplendos: To ſuppreſſe and put to ſilence the haughty doctors, and to ſupplie and correct the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of other men:</hi> As <hi>Ozorius</hi> hath written in his ſecond ſermon vpon the death of father <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> applying vnto their ſociety, the dreames
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8637:25"/>and vaine fancies of the Abbot <hi>Ioachim</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Church. Whereuppon it followes, that they ſubmit all that which concerneth the honor of God, or the good of the Catholike religion, to the particular intereſt of their ſociety, and repute all thoſe for heretikes, which doe not follow their diueliſh opinions, and concurre with them in their ſubtilties, and cunning practiſes.</p>
            <p>This is the reaſon that <hi>Ribadenera</hi> writeth, that <hi>Ignatius Loiola</hi> framed his religion, by reaſon that all the reſt were defectiue: whence it proceedeth, that by the Bulles of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth and ſixth, they haue gotten by way of preuention, all the graces, indulgences, faculties, and priuiledges, which can be found euer to haue beene granted to any, <hi>Antehac conceſſa &amp; concedenda:</hi> A teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that their ambition is not yet at the point where they will ſtay. In their inſtitution they haue wholy derogated from the diſcipline of the Church, and from all the ancient Canonicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, it may be truly ſaide, as the decree of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> hath already pronounced, that they haue built, and raiſed themſelues vpon the ruine, and decay of monaſticall diſcipline. All the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, which ſince the time of our Sauiour Chriſt, haue choſen a kinde of life, ſpeciall, and different from that which is ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Chriſtians, haue made immutable vowes, taken markes, whereby to be diſcerned ſtedfaſt, immoueable, and perpetuall rules. The law of God doth command, that that which is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8637:26"/>dedicated and conſecrated vnto God by the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of a ſolemne vow, ſhould remaine for euer aſſured and ſetled in that eſtate, which is the higheſt degree of perfection that can bee imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: whence it commeth to paſſe, that in things inanimate, and without life, wee cannot make that which is ſanctified, perſeuering in his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, to be vnhallowed, and looſe the force of his conſecration. Farre greater reaſon then is it that a man vowed, dedicated, &amp; conſecrated vnto God, ſhould not looſe this eſſentiall quality, and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from the ſubiect. Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſetting downe the difference betweene a ſimple Vow, and a ſolemne vow, as that of entring into religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, teacheth vs, that the ſolemnity of a vow conſiſteth in the conſecration of him which is vowed, <hi>Quando per certaeregulae profeſsionem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licto ſaeculo &amp; abdicata propria voluntate perfectionis ſtatum aſſumit: When by taking vpon him the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of a certaine rule or Order, forſaking the world, and renouncing his owne will and affections, he doeth aſſume the eſtate of perfection,</hi> which all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines hold cannot be abandoned, nor forſaken without Apoſtaſie. The Ieſuites at the entring into their order, do make a ſolemn vow between the hands of their ſuperior, and a ſolemne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, to liue according to the rules of their ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, the which are of Obedience, Pouerty, &amp; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity; notwithſtanding, by permitting, (as they doe) thoſe of their order to change their forme and manner of life to poſſeſſe goods and riches,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8637:26"/>to ſucceed their anceſtors as heires, and at a need to marry, as many of them haue done, they doe peruert the effect of this infinite obligation, and of a moſt ſolemne vow they make a ſimple one, and giue leaue vnto him, which hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obſerue their rule, and by conſequence that which depends thereupon, to violate the ſame, which is ſo ſtrange, that <hi>Nauarrus</hi> in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries <hi>De Regularibus tom.</hi> 1. ſaith, <hi>hoe eſt nouiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum admirabile, conceſſum praefatae ſocietati: This is an admirable noueltie, granted vnto the aforenamed ſocietie.</hi> If it had beene any where elſe but at <hi>Rome,</hi> he would not haue ſtucke to haue ſaid that this was repugnant to the Diuine and Canon law. And although that there be nothing more natural in all obligations, and bonds, yea the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and moſt preciſe of all, then to be reciprocall and mutuall, that as the people are bound to yeeld fidelity, and obedience vnto their Prince, ſo is he bound likewiſe to giue protection vnto his ſubiects. God himſelfe would not be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when he ſaith, aſſemble me the people of the earth, that they may iudge beweene my people, and me, what thing I ought to haue done for them and haue not done it: And more apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the goſpell, which is full of ſweetnes and mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; whence it proceedeth, that there is no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, receiuing the Vow, and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a religious man, which doth not bind it ſelfe to keepe and maintaine him, in his greateſt extremities, and infirmities; they on the contrary
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8637:27"/>as if they were bound to nothing at all, do expell, and may turne out at their pleaſure, yea, though they haue beene thirty yeeres of their ſociety, thoſe which are weake and ſickly. Whom they either cannot or will not make vſe of any longer.</p>
            <p>Another thing quite contrary to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſcipline is this: By the Buls of <hi>Paul</hi> the third of the yeere. 1543. and of <hi>Iulius</hi> the third, in the yere 1550. they are permitted to change all their rules, and conſtitutions, as often as it ſhall pleaſe their Generall, and he ſhall thinke it to be expedient, for the good of his company, theſe are the very words: <hi>Et tam hactenus fact as quam in poſterum faciendas conſtitutiones, ipſas iuxta locorum ac reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qualitatem mutare, alter are, ſeu in totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; alias de nouo condere poſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt &amp; valeant: And that they haue full power and authoritie according as the condition of the places, and the eſtate of the affaires doe require, to change, alter, or vtterlie to aboliſh all conſtitutions, either heretofore made, or hereafter to bee made, and to make new in their ſtead.</hi> So that as they ſay themſelues, they are neither regular, nor ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, nor are bound to any rule, hauing no other excuſe for this diſſolution, but the deſigne of the abſolute power, which they continuallie point at, &amp; that the temporal power, may giue place to the ſpirituall, for the greater glory of God, as it is ſaide in the ninth part of their conſtitutions, the third chapter and ninth article, <hi>poterit in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad maiorem Dei gloriam, vt ſenſerit, procedere: Hee may proceed in all things as hee ſhall ſee cauſe, ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8637:27"/>it be to the greater glorie of God.</hi> The end of their fourth vow is the moſt exact obedience to the Pope, concerning their miſsions, which they will make vs beleeue is only in regard of Infidels, but on the contrary they themſelues haue written, that this obedience ought to be meaſured, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vnto the motion and will of him, to whom it is promiſed: So that at the inſtant that the Pope ſhall purpoſe, that the Bull <hi>in coena Domini,</hi> ſhould bind the <hi>French men,</hi> and that he would leauie that which they call, and terme, ſufferance, the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites are obliged by their vow to execute it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his meaning, without any other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or moderation, but the will of their Generall, on whom the eſtate and the life of all our Kings by this meanes ſhall depend, an effect of their blind obedience for the perfection whereof they adde, <hi>Imperfecta eſt ea obedientia, in qua, praeter exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutionem, non eſt haec eiuſdem voluntatis &amp; ſententiae, inter eum qui iubet &amp; eum qui obedit, conſenſio: That obedience is vnperfect, wherein, beſides the execution there is not the ſelfe ſame conſent both of will and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in him that commandeth, and the other who obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> hauing no other guide, but the meaning, and will of their Generall which they ought to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute from point to point, and ſay that they are bound to effect it without any knowledge, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, after the manner perchance, as we reade in Victor, in the third booke of the perſecution of the Vandales, that <hi>Hunneric</hi> King of the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales, being ſet on by the perſwaſion of the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8637:28"/>would that all Catholiques ſhould ſweare to that which was conteined in a paper, which was ſealed vp, euen as the Prouincials of the Ieſuites, often times in their aſſemblies, doe cauſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant commands of their Generall to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>And that which is wondrous ſtrange, to the end that they may make the power of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany abſolute, and the power of their Generall more ample then that of the Pope, in that which concerneth their vowes and miſſions, is this, that by the permiſsion of their Generall they may cauſe that to be performed by others, which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined them by the Pope, and it may be reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by their Generall, yea without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and conſent of the Pope, in the ninth part of their Conſtitutions. chap. 3. art. 3. And that which tendeth rather to lay the foundation of a particular greatnes, then to the good of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuerſall Church, they haue obteined Bulles, wherein all men are forbidden, without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any, no not my Lords, the Cardinals to take vpon them any knowledge in the ſecrets of their rule, or to ſound them, although it were to no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe, but to know the truth thereof, as if that from henceforth the diſcourſe, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men were bound to become ſlaues to their vnderſtanding and direction alone: by the Bull of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. decreed in the yeere. 1584. <hi>Ne quis cuiuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſtatus gradus &amp; praeeminentiae exiſtat, dictae ſocietatis inſtitutum, conſtitutiones, vel
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8637:28"/>etiam praeſentes, aut quemuis earum, aut ſupradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium articulorum, vel aliud quid ſupradict a concernnes, quouisdiſputandi, veletiam veritatis inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandae quaeſito colore directè vel indirectè impugnare, veleis contradicere audeat, That no man of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, degree or preheminence whatſoeuer, be ſo bold, as vpon any fained colour, either of diſputation, or of ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out the truth, directly or indirectlie to impugne, or contradict the ordinances and conſtitutions of the ſaid ſocietie, or theſe preſents, or anie article of them, or of all the aforeſaid premiſſes, or anie other thing which may concerne the ſaid premiſſes.</hi> And, that which ſurpaſſeth all beleefe, it attributeth vnto their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall only power to explaine and interpret it as hee ſhall thinke good: which was inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in fauour of them, then when father <hi>Claude Matthew</hi> ſhewed at <hi>Rome</hi> the memories and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances for the haſtning and aduancing of our miſeries and troubles: and they hauing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo cunningly, that of 37. Bulles which they haue obteined, they neuer ſhewed any but thoſe which leaſt ſeemed to fauour them, becauſe they would not diſcouer the great recompences which they receiue for endeuouring to bring the Papal dignity to this height, that there ſhould be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either in the ſpiritualty or temporalty, which ſhould not become ſubordinate vnto it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting only their Generall: for the better effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting whereof, their Bulles containe in them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution from all excommunications which they might incurre <hi>a iure, vel ab homine,</hi> to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8637:29"/>end that no reſpect of duty, or of any obligation whatſoeuer, might retaine and withhold them in ſetting forward this buſineſſe. And as the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites in excuſe of themſelues alleadge that they were not the firſt authors of this abſolute power, <hi>Otho Friſingenſis</hi> hauing obſerued, that it began vnder <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 7. vpon occaſion of the inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitures, and was continued vnder <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 9. ſo are we to admire the ſage prouidence of the Almighty, who preſerued in the ſchoole of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> founded about the ſame time, the treaſure of the truth, contrary vnto that which the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites propoſe vnto vs, as the firſt and chiefe article of our faith.</p>
            <p>The ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> hath alwaies taught, that the primacie of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſours, Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> is by the law diuine, in honor and reuerence whereof the Church, antiquity, &amp; the Chriſtian Princes haue granted and attributed vnto the holy Sea many great priuiledges &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiues which are by the law humane; that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt immediatly after him, and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably ſending forth his Diſciples and Apoſtles gaue vnto them all equally and indiuidually the power of the keies, and that this miſsion is a reall conferring of power, and iuriſdiction, euen as all the members of a naturall body, although they are inequall in dignity, doe proceed immediatlie from nature; by reaſon whereof the eſtate of the Church is Monarchicall, tempered with an Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocraticall gouernement of Biſhops and Prieſts,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8637:29"/>as it were a Senate: the moſt free and perfect e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which that can be imagined. Whence it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth, that the certaine, and infallible authority for the reſolution of points of religion, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in the whole Church, and not in the head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, that by reaſon hereof, Councels are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for the gouernment thereof, the concluſion of whoſe decrees, and Canons, by reaſon of the plurality of voices, the Pope himſelfe is bound to obſerue, without being able to diſpence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, but in caſe, where the Church being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in councell, would haue giuen diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, where it concerneth the good of the vniuerſall Church, and not of particulars, which is the ſolide foundation, whereon the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our Church of <hi>France</hi> are grounded.</p>
            <p>Hence it ariſeth likewiſe, that the decrees, Buls, cenſures, and excommunications of the Popes, yea the Bull <hi>in coena Domint,</hi> and the counſell of <hi>Trent,</hi> as farre as they concerne the ciuill gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do no way binde, nor may be executed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue beene firſt approued, receiued, and publiſhed by the Councell, and Ariſtocraticall order of the Ordinaries of the places, which ought to put them in execution, and cauſe them to be obſerued; that the ſacred elections which ſucceeded the miſsion and vocation immediatlie made by our Sauiour Chriſt, do appertaine vnto the Church both by the law of God and nature, as it appeareth in the 1. and 6. Chapter of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8637:30"/>Acts of the Apoſtles, by the counſels of <hi>Niſe,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> and by the ordinances of our King S. <hi>Lewes,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth. That the Pope is the diſpenſator and Steward, and not Lord of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that he cannot trouble the ordinaries in their functions, nor depriue them of their benefices, without lawfull cauſe, and without the Counſell of the Church, according vnto that which Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> hath written, and is inſerted in the bodie of the Canon law, <hi>can ecce. diſt.</hi> 99. and S. <hi>Bernard</hi> lib. 3. de <hi>conſideratione.</hi> cap. 4. and <hi>Gerſſon</hi> in his booke of the Eccleſiaſtical power conſid, 12. and in the treatiſe which hee hath made concerning the Eſtates of the Church.</p>
            <p>Contrartwiſe the Ieſuites teach, that it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to beleeue that the primacie of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is by the law of God, but that for a more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed gouernment of the Church, we muſt acknowledge a Monarchicall, vniuerſal, abſolute, and infallible power ouer all Chriſtians, yea in that which concerneth the temporalty, for to giue them lawes and directions, yea in Ciuil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters no otherwiſe then doth the reaſonable ſoule rule the body, and affections of man, this is the doctrine of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmin</hi> in his booke <hi>de Rom: Pontifice.</hi> of <hi>Salmeron</hi> in his fourth Tome, and the third part, the fourth treatiſe, explaining that place of Saint <hi>Matthew: Dabo tibi claues regni caelorum, I will giue thee the keies of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</hi> of his commentaries vpon the 13 chapter of the <hi>Romains,</hi> and in the fourth diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8637:30"/>of <hi>Ludouicus Molina</hi> the 2. treatiſe <hi>de iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp; iure,</hi> the 29. diſputation: of <hi>Azorius</hi> in the ſecond part of his morall inſtitutions the 4. book and 19. chapter and of his 21. booke the 3. and 5. chapter of <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> in his commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of <hi>Magallianus</hi> in the beginning of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries of the Eccleſiaſticall Hierarchie, to which abſolute power their principall and moſt ſecret vow, the firſt foundation, and motion of their inſtitution and Order being tied, we haue ſmall reaſon to doubt, but that this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and certaine receiued doctrine of all their ſociety.</p>
            <p>They adde moreouer, that Ieſus Chriſt hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the keies with all Eccleſiaſticall power to S. <hi>Peter</hi> alone, and to his ſucceſſors, for to diſtribute the ſame amongſt the Apoſtles, Biſhops, and Prieſts, according as they ſhal thinke it fit: whence it followeth of neceſſity, that the inſtitution of Biſhops, and Curats is not by the law diuine, and that the Church is a pure ſoueraignty, which ought to depend on the will of the Pope alone, whereupon the Ieſuits found their great power, to the preiudice of Biſhops, Curats, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, taking vpon them more authority ouer the flockes of other men then the Paſtors themſelues. And indeed by the Bulles of <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. of the yeere 76. and 84. beſides that they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the iuriſdiction of all Ordinaries as well ſecular as regular, all command is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, and they are conſtituted to be as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8637:31"/>it were ſuperintendents in the Church, whence it ariſeth, that they vſurpe vpon the charges of all Eccleſiaſticall perſons, bee it either in admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the ſacraments, or in any other function whatſoeuer, &amp; at this day the Penitentiary of my Lord the Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> although it be furniſhed with three moſt ſufficient doctors in diuinity, &amp; renowned for their integrity, yet is it in a manner forſaken &amp; abandoned in reſpect of the Oratory of the Ieſuits, and the Catholike Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land being deſtitute of Biſhops by their monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is depriued of the holy ſacrament of confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Where it is eaſie to be knowne, whether thoſe of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> who haue alwaies mainteined hierarchical order, and the dignity of Biſhops, haue from the yeer 1554. rightly conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured of their deſign, which is to withdraw from the ordinaries the obedience and ſubiection due vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if the Ieſuits may be ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forth as Biſhops and Curates and by this fulneſſe of power, haue more authority then the lawfull paſtors, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould be but as Vicars deſtituable at their pleaſur. <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, that the power was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him not to deſtroy but to edifie, and made ſcruple to preach the Goſpell where Chriſt ſhould haue bin already preached, <hi>ne ſuperalienu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caret. Ro.</hi> 15. &amp; <hi>Rupertus</hi> interpreting the words of <hi>S. Iohn.</hi> 4. chap <hi>Vt cognouit Chriſtus, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith, that the great M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Humility hath taught all the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church &amp; of the houſhold of faith, not to intermeddle with, nor peſter the charges &amp; cures one of another, although that he were the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8637:31"/>ſun &amp; the light it ſelfe, yet he would not manifeſt himſelfe nor ſhine there, where Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> had firſt begun to ſhewe his borrowed light: can it be imagined, that it is poſsible to ſubſtitute one in the place of the father of the familie with the ſame power and authority, as hee hath, to whom nature hath appointed it, or, as <hi>Gerſon</hi> ſaith, that the ordinarie Paſtors which are accountable and anſwerable before God for their flocke, ſhould not haue the guiding and gouernment thereof, to conclude, that a ſtranger ſhould haue more priuacie with the wife, then the lawfull ſpouſe? This is againſt the aduiſe of <hi>Saint Gregory. Non ego honorem eſſe puto</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>in quo fratres honorem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um perdere cognoſco, meus namque honor eſt honor v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſalis Eccleſiae, meus honor fratrum meorum ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus vigor, tune ego vere honoratus ſum, cum ſingulus quibuſque honor debitus non negatur: I doe not thinke any honor to bee done vnto mee in that whereby I know that my brethren looſe their honour, for my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor is the honor of the vniuerſall Church, my honour is the ſoliderigour and courage of my brethren, then am I truly honored, when euery one in particular hath not his due honor and reſpect denied him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi> 3. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid. cap.</hi> 5.</note> And S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>honoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ac dignitatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gradus, &amp; ordines quibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuos ſeruare poſiti eſtis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuidere, You are apointed to preſerue &amp; maintain the degrees &amp; orders of eueryone in his particular place &amp; dignity &amp; not to enuy them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer the Ieſuits doe teach, propoſe, and maintaine, that the Pope only is infallible, the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of Councels is but for decencie onely, <hi>vt facilius canones recipiantur: That the Canons
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8637:32"/>may bee more willingly receiued:</hi> that the Synodall reſolutions doe depend not only of the will of the Pope, but that hee may diſpence with them, change and abrogate them when hee thinketh good, that the ſacred elections are neither from the law of God or nature, and appertaine only to the Pope; Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in the firſt booke <hi>De clericis.</hi> chap. 8. and that hee may diſpoſe of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, yea to the preiudice of the Patrons, and of thoſe vpon whom they are conferred, <hi>etiam ſine cauſa, yea without any cauſe,</hi> the proper tearmes of <hi>Emmanuel Sa in verbo Papa.</hi> That the Buls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, cenſures and excommunications, yea the Bull <hi>in coena Domini,</hi> and the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> in that which concerneth the ciuill Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie doe oblige the French men in conſcience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the French Church neuer gaue conſent thereunto, nor did euer receiue them. <hi>Azorius</hi> in the 5. booke, the 3. chap. of his morall inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. If that the councels doe depend entirely of the authority and approbation of the Pope, as they mainteine, and the author of the Catholike inſtitution perſwadeth, when as in reckoning vp thoſe which are legitimate, hee omitteth thoſe of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and of <hi>Baſil,</hi> which can bee vpon no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground, but for want of being approued and allowed, by the Popes, as <hi>Mariana</hi> his Colleague hath written, it followeth, (and ſee the miſchiefe they runne headlong into,) that all the liberties of the French Church founded vpon the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8637:32"/>of the Councels are ſchiſmaticall, ſince there is an higher aſcendent then that of the Councels, that the appellations which are interpoſed vpon this foundation, are groſſe abuſes and are abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable: it followeth moreouer that the ſacred e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections, haue not their beginning from the law of God, that the Primitiue Church, &amp; the Church of <hi>France,</hi> haue beene in an error vntill the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordate King <hi>Frances</hi> betweene the firſt and Leo the fift, that you (my Lords) doe vſurpe vpon the greateſt part of the iuriſdiction which you haue, and the iuſtice which you ſincerely exerciſe, which the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> attributeth to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons.</p>
            <p>As the doctrine of the Ieſuits peruerteth the Hierarchicall order of the Church, ſo doth it an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate the authority of Princes and of politique lawes, and drowneth it in the ſpirituall power, and is herein as oppoſite and contrary to that which our Theologie doth beleeue as white is vnto blacke, nor the ſenſuall appetite to reaſon, and if that calamities paſt haue not wholy bereft vs of our memorie, we may thinke it to be at this time the miraculous hand of God, which, when wee leaſt thought vpon it, ſeemed to lay open this occaſion, not only to make vs ſee, but alſo feele and touch the cauſe of our ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>The Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris</hi> teacheth, that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall power is no leſſe ſeparated from the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, then heauen is from earth. The raigne of the ſonne of God and of his Vicar our holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8637:33"/>is not of this world: the Church ought not to vſe, (beſide the Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, and that for lawfull cauſes and in ſuch forme and manner as is preſcribed,) any other meanes, but perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not conſtraint, her proceedings, which ought to draw vs to eternall beatitude, are ſimply aduiſe and direction, and not force, and rigor, that it can in no ſort appertaine vnto Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men to meddle in ſecular affaires, all their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling ought to be tied vnto the ſoule and conſcience, and their iuriſdiction vnto thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which follow and depend on the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſacraments.</p>
            <p>That by the law of God and nature, Kings hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding amongſt men the higheſt place next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately vnder God, haue all politique and ciuil power, and that they alone haue power ouer all that which concerneth the temporalty, and amongſt all Princes of the earth our thrice chriſtian Kings, to whom it ſeemeth, that God hath communicated the moſt liuely markes and repreſentation of his image, who doe not auow, nor acknowledge that they hold of any one but God alone, their ſcepter, and their crowne, which he hath had in his ſpeciall protection well nigh from the time that the crowne of the Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of the world hath beene adored. The King of <hi>France</hi> I ſay, who by the teſtimony of the Greeke and Latine Hiſtoriographers, and ſince their time by the Italian writers and doctors is amongſt other Kings as the glorious ſtarre of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8637:33"/>daie in the middeſt of a cloude comming from the South bearing the crowne of glorie and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>Contrary vnto this, the Ieſuits doe ſubmit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the abſolute and infallible Monarchie, which they ſeeke to eſtabliſh, the temporaltie of all Kings and Princes, to the end that the ſpirituall power may reforme, rule and correct them when they abuſe their authority, that is to ſay, when they doe not as the Pope would haue them, and behold their ſophiſtrie, indeed ſay they the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power ought not to meddle directly in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affaires, prouided that they hinder not, or bee no obſtacle to the end and deſigne of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power, or that they cannot ſerue, aide, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the ſame, for if it be ſo, and that there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aduantage to be gotten, <hi>ſpiritualis poteſtas po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt &amp; debet coercere temporalem omni ratione, &amp; via, quae ad id neceſſaria eſſe videtur: The ſpirituall power may and ought to correct the temporall by anie way or meanes whatſoeuer ſhall ſeeme neceſſary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto;</hi> the proper tearmes of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in the 5. booke, <hi>de Rom. Pontif. cap.</hi> 6. This is the Vniuerſall doctrine of all the Ieſuits before cited, and others who haue written, there being ſcarcely any one that hath omitted to handle this ſubiect, which is the principall ſcope and end of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>This is the euill doctrine whoſe fallacious manner of arguing and contrary to all the rules of diſcourſe and diſputation, hatched the troubles
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8637:34"/>of the yeere 1584. in which time the bookes of Cardinall <hi>Bellarmin</hi> were publiſhed, and preached in all corners of <hi>France:</hi> a doctrine of correction, which conſtrained King <hi>Henry</hi> the third of happie memory, who had hazarded his life a thouſand times for the zeale of the Catholique religion, to vſe the remedy which he ſo many times found by experience to be mortall and deadly, forced him to reuoke the Edict of peace vnder which his kingdome and Eſtate of <hi>France</hi> did quietly liue, for to cicatrize to his great griefe ſo dangerous a wounde.</p>
            <p>Let vs not any more deceiue our ſelues; the falſe opinions in religion as they are diſeaſes of the ſoule, ſo ought they to be cured by ſpirituall remedies, the ſubſtance of ſoules which is incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and inuiſible, cannot be conſtrained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue or reiect any thing by force, and therefore thoſe, who thinke to eſtabliſh religion by force, as the Ieſuits, doe wholy forſake and abandon the law and will of God, who would not in the building of the materiall Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the figure of his Church, any one ſtroke ſhould bee giuen with the hammer, or any other toole of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: or that the pretext of religion ſhould driue men into extremities ſo farre different from all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, let vs not attribute vnto ciuill warre the like effect as vnto the word of God, which alone hath power to confirme mens hearts in the truth, and to direct them from the contrary: ſo hath there nothing elſe ariſen from thence, but that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8637:34"/>the ſtrong potion of this Circe of ciuill warre made vs to forget our ſelues and all humanitic.</p>
            <p>And although that both by the law of God and nature, and by humane inſtitution all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects owe faithfull obedience to their Kings and naturall Princes, without that any one of what quality ſoeuer, or by reaſon of any priuiledge whatſoeuer can be freed or exempted.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13 5.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſolum propter iram, ſea propter conſcientiam: Not only for feare but for conſcience,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſcribed both by the ſcriptures, by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the fathers, and by the Canons of the Church: the very bond and ciment of peace betweene the two powers, the influence of the perfect and accompliſhed harmonie of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and rule here on earth, wherein the beſt and firſt Chriſtians being inſtructed, haue alwaies made it their glory to ſerue their Kings cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully whatſoeuer they were, and to accompliſh their commandements in all humble obedience euen vnto the death: yet notwithſtanding all this vpon the doctrine of this abſolute authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of correcting the temporall power, by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, are founded the excommunications a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings, interdictions of their Kingdomes, diſcharging of their people from the oath of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and obedience, in caſe that their naturall and liege Princes ſhould vndertake any thing in temporall matters, contrary vnto the will of the Popes: a doctrine adiuged to be ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call by our Church, the maintainers thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8637:35"/>by the Magiſtrates, conformably vnto that which the French Church reſolued in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Debonnaire, vpon whom <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the fourth would needs make triall of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, the which reſolution was ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined and vpheld by <hi>Hinemarus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Reims</hi> whoſe writings are canonized, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Groſſe againſt Pope <hi>Paſchal</hi> of King <hi>Philip Auguſtus</hi> againſt <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the 3. of <hi>Philip</hi> the faire againſt <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. and likewiſe by the Councell of <hi>Tours</hi> in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding the Ieſuits haue taken no other pretext but this to iuſtifie the vſurpation of the Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> made by <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Spaine</hi> vpon <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Albret,</hi> for no other occaſion, but becauſe hee affiſted the King of <hi>France,</hi> againſt the will of <hi>Iulius</hi> the 2. whom Maſter <hi>Iohn du Tillet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> calleth <hi>perfidioſus ſceleratus, &amp; vecors, perfidious, wicked &amp; fooliſh:</hi> in ſtead that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gilbert Genebrard</hi> a Doctor brought vp in the ſchoole of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> in his Chronologie hath written: <hi>Ferdinandum Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae regem nullo meliore iure, quam quod ſibi vtile &amp; commodum eſſet, regnum Nauarrae expulſo loanne Albreto occupaſſe: That Ferdinand King of Spaine had no better right to poſſeſſe himſelfe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Nauarre by expelling Iohn Albret but that it was fit and commodious for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Frenchmen hath perſeuered in this nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment they had neuer ſucked this outlandiſh
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8637:35"/>poiſon which afterward was diffuſed into their veines, wee had not ſeene the rebellion ſtirred vp againſt our good King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. by this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, confirmed by the booke, whereof <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> was the Author, intituled <hi>Franciſcus Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> publiſhed in the yeere 88. by which (the mindes of the French men being at that time, as they reported ſufficiently diſpoſed and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) it was perſwaded, that the taking of armes againſt a Soueraigne Prince, was lawfull wee had not ſeene ſo many fellowe-Citizens cruelly bent one to the ruine of the other, the heart of this poore Eſtate oppreſſed with ſo many cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, the breſt thereof ſo ſurcharged with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and endurances, and the skinne ſo dried vp, and withered vpon the bones, that there was neither muſcle nor ſinew of this great body which could diſcharge his function, and our Country of <hi>France</hi> a thouſand times as it were at the laſt gaſpe.</p>
            <p>But more then this it had neuer entred into the thought of a French man, if this doctrine had not beene, that it was lawfull to make any attempt vpon the ſacred perſons of Kings, and permitted to kill them: for as they haue taught, that Kings may be excommunicated, and depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if they failed to ſubmit themſelues vnto the will of this abſolute power, ſo they haue alſo ſaid, that it was meritorious to kill them, and by the one haue proued the other, this is the courſe they take to proue it. Princes by being excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8637:36"/>condemned and depoſed of publique perſons become priuate and particular men, without hauing either authority, or ſubiects: and ſo from being Kings they become tyrants, vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and perturbers of the common peace and repoſe. <hi>Occupantem tyrannicè poteſtatem quiſque de populo poteſt occidere, ſi aliud non ſit remedium, eſt enim publicus hoſtis: Emanuel Sa in verbo Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Any one of the common people whatſoeuer may kill him who tyrannically vſurpeth the authority, if there be no other remedy, for he is a publike enemie.</hi> The obiect of all the enterpriſes made by <hi>Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides,</hi> vpon which ground both Cardinall <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> in his Apologie againſt the King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, pag. 299. and <hi>Ioannes Mariana</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de rege &amp; regis inſtitutione,</hi> and the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its likewiſe author of the booke intituled <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheatrum honoris,</hi> haue all after one manner praiſed the abhominable parricide of our poore Prince, and the Ieſuits of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> haue both ſaide and written, that this was the cauſe of their ſafety, which this very doctrine the raſhnes of <hi>Barriere</hi> was armed in the yeere 1593. ſtreng the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Counſell of <hi>Varrade Rector</hi> of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits againſt our inuincible King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth. At which time father <hi>Commolet</hi> did egge him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by his outcries,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.15.</note> deſiring an <hi>Ehud</hi> of what quality ſoeuer he were, beleeuing that <hi>Barriere</hi> could not faile of his enterpriſe, or, if he did, that he would ſtirre vp the minde of ſome other to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the like.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:8637:36"/>
            <p>A great misfortune that <hi>France</hi> hath loſt this aduantage which in ancient time was attributed vnto her, that ſhee nouriſhed no monſters. But God ſtirred vp his Hercules, to the end that he might ſubdue them, of whoſe hand next after his bountie he would wee ſhould receiue this diuine worke, and the miracle of the riſing againe of this Eſtate.</p>
            <p>In this time the Ieſuits knew that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted nothing which could any more be oppoſed againſt the victorious armes of our great King, that hee was as certainely aſſured of the honour of conquering his Kingdome, as that it iuſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained vnto him, they made ſhew, as if they would take a ſweeter and more pleaſing tune, and for to vphold and preſerue their ſociety, publiſhed the reſolution which they ſaid their Generall had made at <hi>Rome</hi> in the end of the yeere. 1593. by the which they were expreſlie forbidden to intermeddle with any affaires, they proteſted to obey the ſame, and to renounce all factions, to honor and ſerue the King as Subiects, whoſe clemencie ſhould more appeare in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m all, then in the remnant and ſurplus of thoſe who had ſwarued and ſtraied from their duty, this is that which then they touched in their pleading, and by their defenſe put in print, and it may bee, was the onely reaſon and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that they were not at that time depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Kings grace and pardon.</p>
            <p>The wiſdome of the Ieſuits conſiſteth in gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8637:37"/>time vpon ſuch occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their deſigne neuer dying, they attend the commodity that their ſeed may bring forth fruit in ſeaſon: foure or fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths after, at the inſtant that the King left his armie, this Prince, the Pourtrait of valour it ſelfe; in the midſt of two hundred gentlemen, in his houſe of the Louure is wounded by <hi>Chaſtel,</hi> a ſcholler of the Ieſuits, nouriſhed in their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and hurt in ſuch ſort, that without the manifeſt prouidence of God, who loued vs, at that time this Monarchie had beene vtterlie ſubuerted, and we miſerable men had beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the bleſſings which hee afterwardes obtained for vs, by his incomparable valor, his iuſtice, and piety, no leſſe admired at by all the world, then his arme and his ſword were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted.</p>
            <p>This miſerable monſter, in the preſence of you, my Lords, ſaid hee ought elſe but that the King, although he were a Catholike, was yet out of the Church, that he yet ſtood excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that he muſt be ſlaine: is there any thing here to bee ſeene differing from their propoſitions? <hi>Barriere</hi> had ſaid as much before, <hi>Guignard</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite written it, and after a thouſand blaſphemies vttered againſt his naturall Prince, <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. added this moreouer againſt the laſt King. <hi>If hee cannot be depoſed without warre, let armes be taken againſt him: if that cannot be done; let him bee killed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True enemies of quiet and repoſe, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the diſciples of our Sauiour Ieſus
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8637:37"/>Chriſt, who vſed no other armes but their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: and preached nothing but loue, charity, and concord. Your enterpriſes againſt our Kings and their Crownes, by your owne confeſsion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued a greater condemnation then that which was pronounced againſt you by the decrees, what tongue can ſufficiently praiſe the power and effects of the Iuſtice of this great Parliament, which in the middeſt of the greateſt tempeſts, hath alwaies meaſured her actions by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the good, and honour of this Eſtate? not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all oppoſitions your glory ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine immortall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Politickes</hi> holdeth an opinion which hath beene followed by many others, that there are ages in the which God in perſon ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the Sterne of this Vniuers, doth guid and turne it according to his good pleaſure; but that againe there are other times in which God negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth this gouerment, and that then the world deſtitute of the conduct of his creator taketh a motion contrary vnto that which God gaue it: ſo that the Eaſt commeth to be the Weſt, and the North taketh the place of the South; and that when this vniuerſall conuerſion doth happen, the generations, faſhions, and manners of men, are either extinct or changed. As Chriſtians we are brought vp in a better ſchoole, and fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued that the prouidence of God neuer aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth the guiding and conduct of the worlde, and doth not in any age permit the Intelligences
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8637:38"/>or Angels which moue the celeſtiall ſpheres, to depart from the motion and meaſure which hath beene once preſcribed them, notwithſtanding when calamities raigne in the world, it ſeemeth that God ſleepeth, and that he will meddle no more with ought, the rebellion of the people ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with all kind of vices, with forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards God; and all ſorts of miſeries and calamities during the ciuill warre, had taken ſo deepe roote: and ſo ſtrange and maruellous a growth.</p>
            <p>On the contrary with the acknowledgement of our King, our Soueraigne, and lawfull Prince: with the concord of vs who are fellow-Citizens, and his Subiects; as God more properly made vs to ſee his preſence and his gouernment, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he made vs feele his bounty; neuer was there more affection in each one to performe his duty; more deuotion toward his Prince: more grace in particular, more hope of future times, it ſeemed that the ſoules of all Frenchmen looſed out of priſon, enioyed ſuch a liberty as neuer could bee expected or hoped for.</p>
            <p>There had beene more ſpent in ſeeking to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poile our King of his rightfull inheritance, then euer was in making warre againſt the Turke: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe all the iniuries which he had receiued from the time of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. and his ſucceſſours vntill <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. could not withold him from diſcharging the duty of a thrice Chriſtian King, from ſacrificing al his paſsions and iuſt apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8637:38"/>of the wrongs hee had receiued to the glory of God, and the good of his people. Thus our King, whileſt hee liued exalted aboue the moſt renowned Emperors; richer then euer Prince was in the loue of his people, had the good will of all his ſubiects equally, and as he was all our hope; ſo was he the terror of all our enemies.</p>
            <p>And that which made the bleſsing of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, was, that neuer there were ſo good courſes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and greater ſucceſſe in the conuerſion of thoſe which were out of the Church: in priuate there were ſuch mild communications, ſuch mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; and endeauors for the honor of God, and of the Catholique Church: and ſo viſible an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the holy ſpirit, that thoſe who were not yet touched, were more aſtoniſhed then gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or diſpleaſed thereat. What was the ſucceſſe of the conference at <hi>Fountaine-bleau</hi> where the King himſelfe was moderator, and did giue light vnto others by his example; as the light in the middeſt of the Temple: where that learned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, that moſt illuſtrious Cardinal, that minde enriched with immortall graces, by his Chriſtian temper did more profit the Catholique religion, then ten thouſand Ieſuits could euer doe by their preaching of fire &amp; ſword? O what victories were there in publike of the greateſt wits, from whom the holy Sea and all Chriſtendome hath receiued moſt notable ſeruices, what in priuate and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of thoſe who wanted rather oportunitie then will.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:8637:39"/>
            <p>The perfection of a man conſiſteth in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the truth, there is nothing which ſo much tempereth the inconſiderate zeale of thoſe who are in an error, as to ſhew them, that no other force ſhall bee vſed vpon their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but that of the truth: and as the King did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly endeauour it, hauing eſtabliſhed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique religion, and made the maſſe to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in more then three hundred Townes of his Kingdome, where it had not been ſaid in fiue and thirty or fortie yeeres before, ſo did he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the accompliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this holy worke in the conuerſion of the greateſt of his Eſtate, and of his neighbor Princes, who ſuffered themſelues to be perſwaded both by the force of reaſon, and by the miracle of his example.</p>
            <p>The holy ſcripture teacheth vs, that too curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and nice deuiding cauſeth ſchiſme, the Church hath felt the diſcommodity thereof; too much vniting is the other extremity which threatneth the like inconuenience: All the body is not the eie, ſaith the Apoſtle, for then what ſhould become of the hearing? and the body is not one member, but many: God hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the body of ſuch a temperature that he would haue the members to haue care perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally one of another: that which delaieth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of an infinite company of men ſeparated from the Church, although they are ſatiſfied in all other points of the Catholike faith, is this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power and authority which they cannot
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8637:39"/>brooke, this is that which augmenteth their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, and ſuſpitions and putteth off the reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of many; this is the meane whereby the Ieſuits haue ouerthrowen the eſtate of <hi>Hungarie,</hi> made the Turke maſter of the better part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that the reſt is held but at his pleaſure, this hath troubled <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> bred diſorder and confuſion in <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> without that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie part of the worlde can be free from this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the profitable ſeruices, which the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits doe vnto the Church; who for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this power, and for their particular ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doe make as ſmall conſcience to hurt the beſt Catholikes, as thoſe whom they hold to be ſeparated from the Church, that they may veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a part of the decree of the Sorbonne, <hi>Multas in populo querelas, multas lites, aemulationes, diſsiaia, contentiones, variaque ſchiſmata inducit: That it bringeth in many quarrels among the people, much ſtrife, aemulation, diſcord and contention, and diuers ſchiſmes:</hi> not to repeate the example of our laſt troubles, when they would from the beginning abridge King <hi>Henry</hi> the third a Prince moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike of his ſeruants, yea ſo farre forth as to deny them the holy Communion. The ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> hath felt their calumnie, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Bellarmin</hi> hauing written in the 4. booke de <hi>Rom. Pont.</hi> chapter 1. &amp; 2. that the opinion of the ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> which doth not auow the abſolute and infallible power, <hi>erat erronea &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſi
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8637:40"/>proxima.</hi> Nay rather is it not hereſie to doubt of the faith of the ſchoole of <hi>Paris?</hi> It is true, that for proofe of his propoſition he allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a paſſage of Deuteronomy chap. 17. which (I very much grieue that this occaſion enforceth to ſpeake it,) hee hath corrupted, for whereas it is in all the editions of the Bibles, yea, in that which was receiued and imprinted by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth, according to the text of the tongues <hi>Venieſque ad Sacerdotes Leuitici generis &amp; ad iudicem qui fuerit illo tempore, quaereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ab eis, qui indicabunt tibi iudicii veritatem. And thou ſhalt come vnto the Prieſts of the Leuits, and to the Iudge that ſhall be in thoſe daies: and ſhalt enquire of them, and they ſhall ſhew thee the truth of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> He hath written <hi>ad Sacerdotem,</hi> againſt the expreſſe prohibition of the holy ſpirit, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth vs to change or diminiſh any thing from the booke of life. The ſelfe ſame happened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Author of the Catholike inſtitution the ſecond booke 8. chapter, vpon the like ſubiect, where citing the place of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> chapt. 22. <hi>Ego autem rogaui pro te Petre vt non deficiat fides tua, &amp; tu aliquando conuerſus confirma fratres tuos. But I haue praied for thee Peter, that thy faith faile not, and when thou art conuerted, ſtrengthen thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:</hi> he tranſpoſeth this word <hi>aliquando</hi> from one period vnto another, and writeth: <hi>Ego rogaui prote Petre, vt non aliquando deficiat fides tua,</hi> abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this word <hi>aliquando</hi> for <hi>nunquam.</hi> But they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8637:40"/>doe not this wrong to the ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> alone, there is no Eccleſiaſticall order nor Religion which they haue not gone about publikely to diſgrace, who knoweth not what their ambition hath coſt the Catholique Church of England, which they had welnigh vndone in ſtead of ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it? After the deceaſe of Cardinall <hi>Alan</hi> the conducting of the Engliſh Seminaries was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto the Ieſuits, preſently they meditated how they might take from the Prieſts and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall men of the Country, whoſe deuotion and affection had beene prooued, the rule and authority from ouer their flocke, for to attribute it vnto themſelues, cauſed Arch-prieſts to bee made which ſhould yeeld them a reaſon of all things, and would that the contributions and almes of the Country, which are not ſmall, ſhould be diſtributed by their hands, which cauſed more trouble amongſt thoſe poore Catholiques, then all their perſecution, in the which, before they medled with matters, there was neuer any obiect of committing treaſon: yea they came to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe that ſome Eccleſiaſticall men of England, hauing paſſed the Sea for to aduertiſe his holines of this diſorder <hi>Perſons</hi> the Ieſuite made them to be put in priſon, and to be handled as male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors and ſchiſmatikes, and hindered their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peales from being receiued.</p>
            <p>Theſe poore men thus afflicted found meanes by the Councell of the Vniuerſity of Paris, to make the iuſtice of their complaint to appeare,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8637:41"/>whereupon came forth the <hi>Breue</hi> of Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> the 8. by which the Eccleſiaſticall men of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land were forbidden to render any account of their adminiſtration, vnto the Ieſuits, or to their Generall, nor to communicate their affaires vnto them by letters or otherwiſe, but to addreſſe themſelues, directly to his holineſſe, with reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that which Cardinal <hi>Caietan</hi> protector of England, had decreed in fauour of them, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concerning the diſtribution of the almes: and after that, the trouble of that Church ceaſed, and the peace thereof had continued longer, had it not beene for the negotiations of the Ieſuits, in that which rather concerned the Monarchie of the world, then the Kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>Another example without exception, and the carriage whereof was publike and notorious, a teſtimony of the mediocrity, whereof they boaſt that they haue gotten the perfection, and of the peace which they procure vnto the Church. The inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was placed in the hands of the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans, as well for their great and excellent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as for the great ſeruices they had done the Catholike Church, time hath not diminiſhed the ancient and firſt glory of this order. The Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, whoſe deſigne tendeth to the ſoueraigne dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Church, bethought themſelues to ſtirre vp againſt them a diſpute which they call <hi>de auxillijs,</hi> concerning iuſtification: thinking that by getting ſome aduantage vpon the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of theſe Religious men leſſe cunning
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8637:41"/>then they are, it would bee eaſie to pull out of their hands this powerfull function, although they neuer had abuſed the ſame. Which Pope <hi>Clement</hi> vnderſtanding forbad the diſputation, notwithſtanding the Ieſuits publiſhed the ſame: and there is no man who is ignorant, that this wiſe and holy Pope deſired to abate their ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, confeſſing that hee had entred into ſpeech thereof, with Cardinall <hi>Tolet,</hi> who preferred towards his latter end the honor and good of the Church, before the factions of his ſociety; that he had ſought meanes to make the counſell of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth to preuaile, which was to ſhut them vp, and to ſubmit their Generall to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitular reſolutions of the ſociety, and to make him triennall, from the which that they might ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelues, they haue obtained a Bull from Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the foureteenth, which importeth excommunication to all thoſe who ſhould offer to enterpriſe the like: but the Pope being not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to bring it to paſſe, and Cardinall <hi>Tollet</hi> being deceaſed, he would, vnder colour of reforming their Order, haue ſent their Generall into <hi>Spaine,</hi> which the Ieſuits withſtood, affirming vnto his Holineſſe, that he could not do it without preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his health, which made one amongſt them to enquire of a woman which was poſſeſſed with an euill ſpirit, what ſhould be the ſucceſſe of that voyage, doubting with others of his ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that this was a meane to diminiſh the power
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8637:42"/>of <hi>Aquauiua</hi> which is as great at <hi>Rome</hi> as that of the Pope.</p>
            <p>The leauen which the Ieſuits had left in the Townes where the Kings Edict touching there baniſhment was not executed, made them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to encreaſe the hope of their returne, hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the witneſſe of time, the memorie of ages paſt, the mirror of men, the meſſenger of all the accidents which declare the truth, ſhall faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully report vnto poſterity, that they haue not omitted ought which might make for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and they haue not concealed it, in a great diſcourſe compoſed of thirty or fourty articles which they publiſhed, and ſuppoſed it to haue been made in the yeere 1603. by the King, in anſwere to the graue remonſtrances of his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they impoſe and thruſt vpon ſtrange nations as if it were true, hauing made it to bee printed in Latin and Italian, and lately <hi>Gretſerus</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> for their laſt diſcharge, and alſo <hi>Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin,</hi> doe imploy it in their Bibliotheca or Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle which they haue compoſed, to the end that this impoſture ſhould paſſe current vnto poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: who after that they had beene ſo bold as to compare their reeſtabliſhment which was of pure and meere grace, vnto the diuine and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eſtabliſhment of our King in his Eſtate, yet they confeſſe that they obtained it as they might, &amp; very hardly. As we all acknowledge that the clemency of our King hath giuen peace to his people, ſo it was neceſſary for him to aſſure the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8637:42"/>foundations thereof by iuſtice, in caſe of ſo great, ſo inueterate and pernicious a corruption, &amp; for the ſure eſtabliſhment of the common weale not to content himſelfe to command wel, but to inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite the committing of euill. Great King which haſt beene without compariſon more exalted in vertue then in dignity, aboue other men, your good ſeruants wounded by the knife which hath ſhortened your daies, ſhall for euer complaine that your vnmeaſured clemencie and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath encreaſed the boldneſſe of thoſe who haue beene to you as very infidels, as you haue beene vnto them a good and gracious King.</p>
            <p>Our heart was ſound, our wound recouered and the griefe of the Vniuerſity in particular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to breake away, when the Ieſuits emploied the interceſsion of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. about their reeſtabliſhment in this kingdome. All Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can be witneſſe of the deuotion which our King did beare towards the holy Sea, and of the honour which hee gaue particularlie vnto Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> for his high, great, and eminent vertues: the bounty of the King more reſpected the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the Pope, and the aſſurance which he gaue him, then the naturall apprehenſion of the iniuries and outrages which he had receiued, ſo that after manie commandements vnto you, my Lords, and many remonſtrances by you, the letters which they had obteined were verified, it being worth the noting that the conditions ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto their reeſtabliſhment, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8637:43"/>men thought to bring them to the tearmes of ſimple religious men, and obedient Subiects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſented and agreed vnto by the Pope, were not allowed by their Generall, by reaſon that they were different from the principall rules of their Order, they kept cloſe this ſecret from vs, by the which they thought themſelues to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with, from all that which was required of them, and from that which they promiſed, not being able to be bound without the conſent, and will of the Generall, they being more bound vnto him then vnto God; the Church, or Pope, or to all the world beſide. They were reeſtabliſhed in the moneth of Ianuary 1604. and a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, their brethren of Doway had managed the enterpriſe vpon the perſon of Duke <hi>Maurice,</hi> and had ſent their Purueior named <hi>Panne</hi> to execute it. And a ſhort time after was diſcouered ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſigne of their good intentions, to wit the conſpiracy of the which three of their fathers <hi>Teſmond, Gerard</hi> and <hi>Garnet,</hi> had the managing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of England, and all the Eſtates and Magiſtrates of the country, the moſt prodigious that euer could enter into the heart of man, and which ſurpaſſeth and confoundeth all the exceſſe and villany of former times. The Eſtates of England were ſummoned, the place and day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and the ouerture prepared: the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors had found meanes to fill the vault vnder the roome where the aſſembly ſhould haue beene, with ſuch a quantity of gunpowder, hidden and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8637:43"/>couered with wood, that with the leaſt artifice, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as far off as they liſted, they could haue blown vp &amp; ouerthrown a whol kingdom at one inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: they themſelues haue thus deſcribed it, and part of thoſe which were guilty, haue confeſſed it: It is not the meane to eſtabliſh the Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to fill an Eſtate with murders and horrible combuſtion, it is rather the way to giue cauſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heretikes, ſtifly to bend themſelues againſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſo contrary to moderation and mildnes, which God hath left as a marke of his light, and to make that the Chriſtian verity neuer returne more thither from whence it hath beene expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that it come to paſſe, that infidelity and paganiſme ſhall rather ſucceed hereſie, then that euer there ſhould be any amendment or reſtoring of that which is better.</p>
            <p>From this eſtabliſhing of the ſpirituall power aboue the temporall, proceedeth this other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the doctrine of the Ieſuits, to wit, that Eccleſiaſticall men are neither ſubiects, nor vnder the iuriſdiction of any Prince, but of the Pope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yea in that which concerneth temporall matters, that liuing in the Eſtate of any one what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, they are not bound by the lawes nor po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies, be they fundamentall and moſt ſupreme: and therefore <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>de Clericis</hi> from the 28. chapter to the 30. <hi>Emmanuel Sa</hi> in his Confeſsionary vpon the word <hi>Clericus, Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerus</hi> in his writings againſt the common-wealth of Venice, doe concurre, together with all the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8637:44"/>reſt of their ſociety, that although Eccleſiaſticall men ſhould conſpire againſt the Eſtate or perſon of the Prince, yet they cannot encurre the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Treaſon, becauſe he is neither King nor Prince as to them, neither are they ſubiects in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him.</p>
            <p>The ſchoole of <hi>Paris</hi> on the contrary hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies held and taught, that Eccleſiaſticall men as naturall ſubiects of the Princes and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, in the which it hath pleaſed God they ſhould be borne, are bound in the ſelfe ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as other men are to obey the lawes of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſtraint, and are exempt only in regard of that which concerneth Gods diuine ſeruice, and the competent maintainance of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Eſtate: and as to this point the Ieſuits diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute fallaciouſly, going from the declaration of a very ſpeciall and particular exemption to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire generall and abſolute immunity, contrary vnto the doctrine of the Church, who teacheth vs that as the feare of God is the beginning of wiſdome, ſo the feare of the Magiſtrate is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of diſcretion, that as this life is the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of the life eternall, ſo the lawes of Princes and Kingdomes are a figure of the eternall law: ſo that he that loueth not the figure ſheweth that he loueth yet leſſe the thing figured.</p>
            <p>This exemption continuing it is not to bee doubted but that Eccleſiaſticall men, ſhould be as it were ſo many garriſons of ſtrangers in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: and if the Prince or magiſtrate would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8637:44"/>them to anie thing for the good of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, it ariſeth from the ſame learning, that in as much as they are not his ſubiects, he ſhould be a tyrant and an vſurper, which might be depoſed and killed by any one whoſoeuer: This was the foundation of the trouble which we haue ſeene ſtirred vp againſt the common-wealth of <hi>Venice,</hi> euer moſt Catholique, and deuoted to the holie Sea, which cannot bee attributed to any but the Ieſuits, whom the Senate of that common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in honor of the Catholique religion had carefully cheriſhed fifty or threeſcore yeeres in ſuch ſort that foure or fiue yeeres before, they had beſtowed a great Pallace vpon them for their Colledge, where they had aboue three hundred ſchollers, children of the beſt houſes of <hi>Venice,</hi> and poſſeſſed in this Eſtate twelue or fifteene thouſand crownes a yere reuenues. During the Papacie of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Venicians had pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed an ordinance by the which Eccleſiaſticall men were inhibited from acquiring any immoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, this holy father knew it well inough with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therat. And how could he take it in euil part ſince that in the Eſtate of <hi>Milan</hi> there was the like prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrictly obſerued, &amp; that the Pope that now is vpon his firſt comming vnto the Popedome, had forbidden the houſe of <hi>Loretta</hi> to purchaſe any more immoueables: the Ieſuits being deſirous neuertheleſſe to purchaſe a Pallace of pleaſure vpon the riuer of <hi>Brent</hi> neere vnto the City, were hindered by this law, ſo as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8637:45"/>the gentlewoman which was owner thereof drew backe, and ſaid, that ſhe had been ſeduced by her Confeſſor. This nouriſhed in their minds an euill will towards the State: ſo that two Eccleſiaſticall men of <hi>Vincence</hi> being impriſoned for moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible crimes, the Ieſuits, taking their time, gaue aduertiſement vnto the Pope, that theſe were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes vpon his authority, and of thoſe who depended immediately on him; that the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had no power to make lawes, which ſhould concerne Eccleſiaſticall men, although they were neceſſary for their Eſtate and conſeruation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the will and conſent of the Pope, neither to decree any thing without making him firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewithall; thus doing, they tooke from them all ſoueraigntie, they perſwaded the excommunication with all earneſtneſſe, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cardinall <hi>Zapata,</hi> protector of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, for confirmation of their counſell ſaid, that this action done for the greatnes of the Church, merited a ſtatue of gold, dedicated to immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This firſt breach gaue apprehenſion of great calamities to enſue, ſo that the Pope naturallie deſirous of mild and gentle courſes, and enclined thereunto by the counſell of the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and ſpecially of that of our great King, was againe exaſperated by the Ieſuits, and by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which they wrote vnto their Generall, who hath no ſhew of a religious man beſides his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite, and behaueth himſelfe in all his actions as one who would raiſe ſome great Empire: they
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8637:45"/>promiſed that the Senate would be diuided, and that the people would riſe, that the ſchollers which they had were as ſo many priſoners, and aſſurances of their promiſes, that the excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication ſhould haue the like effect at <hi>Venice</hi> as at <hi>Ferrara:</hi> and vpon this was the interdict pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
            <p>The common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> contented it ſelfe in this occurrence, to forbid all Eccleſiaſticall men to trouble the ſtate of mens conſciences, and to take from them all occaſion of excuſe, gaue the religious men choiſe to ſtay, or to retire them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the Ieſuits made anſwere, that they would conforme themſelues to the ordinances of the common-wealth: in the meane time they ſecretly ſend father <hi>Poſſeuin</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> to their General, and vnder hand labor to ſuborne other Eccleſiaſticall men, and to hinder their obedience due vnto their Soueraigne.</p>
            <p>There fell out an action very memorable of a good religious man accuſtomed to plaine honeſt dealing, which had no other end but the loue of God, and not the care of worldly affaires, or of rule and gouernment: the Prouinciall of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchins,</hi> a man of ſingular integrity, and of a holie life, who wrote vnto all the Couents of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that if the Prince &amp; common-wealth ſhould command any thing contrary vnto the twelue Articles of the Creede, they were rather to ſuffer a thouſand deathes, then to obey it: but that in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8637:46"/>whatſoeuer thing elſe ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded them, they ſhould diſcharge the duty of good ſubiects without any ſcruple of conſcience, vpon paine of his indignation, the which they ought to feare as much as death it ſelfe. True holineſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſsimulation or ambition, which ſhall crown the glory of this obedience with immortality, which, in deſpite of theſe new doctrines, the wind of truth ſhall blow into all corners of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world.</p>
            <p>There paſſed not many daies before that there were fathers and husbands which complained that their wiues and children made a doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhould yeeld them the loue and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence due vnto them, being afrighted by the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits who preached that they were excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and damned: and notwithſtanding that at their departure from <hi>Venice,</hi> they had burned a great quantity of their papers, fearing leaſt they ſhould be ſeene, neuertheleſſe there were found ſome bearing wirneſſe, that they kept a regiſter of the confeſsions of men of quality, and that they had ſent a great maſſe of money vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> and carried away all the ornaments which had beene giuen to their Churches, and at <hi>Padua</hi> and <hi>Breſſe</hi> where they were ſurpriſed and had not leaſure to diſpoſe of their papers, nor to burne them, there were found ſo many enquiries and ſearches of the diſpoſition of the Eſtate, and of all the families in particular, that it was a moſt infallible token that they had ſome great deſigne in hand, to the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8637:46"/>execution whereof was required ſo painefull a curioſity.</p>
            <p>It is another ſecret very remarkeable: that they ſtirred vp this trouble in the Eſtate of <hi>Venice,</hi> then when the Count de Fuentes had an armie on foot in <hi>Italie</hi> for the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two great forts to be built which are held im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable, for to hinder the paſſage of the Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers and the Griſons; by meanes whereof they thought aſſuredly in them ſelues, that theſe forces &amp; their directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s meeting, they might haue tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that Eſtate, as they did that of <hi>Portugal,</hi> firſt by the vanity wherewith they knew how to puffe vp the mind of the King, <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> to his ruin and vtter ouerthrow, who had ſuffered them to beare authority in his Eſtate: then by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the affection of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall his ſucceſſour from <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Bragance</hi> husband vnto <hi>Catherine</hi> his neece, and daughter of <hi>Edward</hi> his brother, which had excluded <hi>Iſabel</hi> from whom the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> was deſcended, to make vſe of it in his behalfe, and in ſtrengthening his pretention, and likewiſe by the warre which they kindled againſt <hi>Don Antonio</hi> acknowledged to be their naturall and lawfull Prince, in the which they ſpared not the blood of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand good Religious men, loyall vnto their King, by reaſon whereof there was obtained a Bul of ſpeciall abſolution.</p>
            <p>For beſide that the ſtocke and race of him who was the founder of the Ieſuits is Spaniſh, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8637:47"/>their Generals of the ſame nation, or of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther country ſubiect vnto the King of Spaine, which inſpireth into them a particular affection vnto that Eſtate: they aiming at no other marke, but the abſolute eſtabliſhment of the ſpirituall power wherewith they promiſe readily to cruſh and beate down hereſies, haue more need of force then perſwaſion, and doe rather chuſe to make vſe of the materiall ſword then the ſpirituall: now the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> being hee who moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth himſelfe vnto this deſigne, they ſeek to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt him aboue all other Princes: and indeed they haue written that the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the ſift and King <hi>Philip</hi> did well conforme themſelues vnto this reſolution, but that they were hindered by the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> without whom hereſie had beene quite rooted out: they ſay that King <hi>Frances</hi> the firſt made alliance with the Turke, that <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond defended the Proteſtants, whom the Emperor would haue deſtroied, that <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. made alliance with the Queene of England, Germaines, and Switzers: that Spaine hath receiued the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and cauſed the inquiſition to the ſtrictly obſerued.</p>
            <p>Great ingratitude! are there any Princes in the world that haue ſo much exalted the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion as the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and which haue more augmented the holy Sea? the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Pepin</hi> and <hi>Charlemaine</hi> falſly attributed vnto <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the armes of <hi>France</hi> ſo often tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported into the holy land, thoſe of king <hi>Lewis</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:8637:47"/>the 12. and of his ſucceſſors emploied in reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the Popes eſtate which was vſurped on, all this is nothing to thoſe who preferre their nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties before any other conſideration, and are bound to take it in euill part, that the thrice chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings of <hi>France</hi> for the conſeruation of their Eſtate haue maintained the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the fiſt, and neuer blame the alliance which he bought with King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. of England, for to ruinate and ſubuert vs.</p>
            <p>And for proofe of this their affection conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt vs, thoſe which haue gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them do report, that they obſerue this order, that in euery houſe there are two which keep regiſters, &amp; haue the charge of matters of Eſtate, to whom the reſt doe confeſſe themſelues, and are bound to report what they learne; this is carried by the Viſiters vnto their Generall, (and he muſt be a Neapolitane, Sicilian, or Spaniarde,) to giue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe thereon.</p>
            <p>And in the yere 1604 there being diſcouered a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fraternity of Ieſuits aſſociated, (as they ſay) that a whole Towne may be Ieſuited) who made their aſſembly in the houſe of the Ieſuits in the City of <hi>Genua,</hi> in the which thoſe of the brotherhood had ſworne not to giue their voices for the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Magiſtrates and publike officers, to any but thoſe of their fraternity, the Common-wealth hauing greatly conteſted againſt ſuch a monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and being reſolued to haue expelled the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, they ſaid that they had done it, becauſe ſome
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8637:48"/>of the Towne had intelligence with the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſeemed to affect and fauour them.</p>
            <p>But the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> hath not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any excuſes for their enterpriſes, nor like vnwiſe men ſtaied from digging and making hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their wels vntil they were ready to die for thirſt: for after that they had beene enformed of their carriage, of their ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which they made in the Townes adioining vnto their Eſtate, &amp; of the calumnies and ſlanders which they ſpred againſt the Duke <hi>Leonardo Donato,</hi> whoſe innocencie and piety are known and renowned as well as his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, made a decree whereby the Ieſuits were perpetually and irreuocably baniſhed out of their Eſtate, not leauing them any hope euer to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate or thinke of their eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>And God being ſo pleaſed, that our great King ſhould be the author of peace in the South as well as in the North, the Ieſuits only were exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the benefit of this vniuerſall reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this ſage Commonwealth ſo well knew how to reliſh and make vſe of the deliuerance from the danger it was fallen into, that it would rather haue choſen warre, then to haue made peace ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Ieſuits.</p>
            <p>Oh! would to God we had not been ſo credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, that we had been as ſeuere within our ſelues, as ſtrong and puiſſant abroad, that for to refreſh the liuer we had not cooled and taken away the heate of our ſtomackes, we ſhould not haue been the diſcourſe of all nations of the Earth, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8637:48"/>of their pity and commiſeration, the proofe of what they ſaid, to wit, that the Ieſuits compaſſe great and weighty enterpriſes by taking hold of ſmall aduantages, &amp; vnlikely to doe hurt; we had then been ignorant of their rare doctrines which they haue both preached and publiſhed, as that it was more meritorious to pay tribute and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, then to giue almes, that a man may blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme without committing mortall ſinne, that Ladies may lawfully paint and farde themſelues, yea for to pleaſe the world, that vſury is lawfull, and by the ſame rule theft ſhould be tolerable, ſo it were to beſtow in almes; that it is no ſimony to giue mony for benefices; <hi>Modoid fiat non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pretium, ſed tanquam motiuum ad reſignandum, vel tanquam motiuum aliquod gratuitum: So it bee giuen not as a price, but as a motiue to reſigne, or ſome motiue of free will and of gratuitie:</hi> the proper termes of <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> vpon the Summe of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Tome 3. diſput. 4. queſtion 16. page 3. fol. 2039. wee had neuer learned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence good with euill, nor the forme of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatory co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſions, being all but ſuperficial cures of vices, things vnbeſeeming true religious men.</p>
            <p>We had not ſcene in theſe our daies (horrible things) interrogatories framed for to learne of her, which was ſaid to be poſſeſſed with an euill ſpirit, the truth of the doctrine, and difficult pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſcripture, ill curioſities forbidden in the 18 chapter of Deuteronomy, and alſo by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell held at <hi>Narbonne</hi> vpon paine of excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8637:49"/>and <hi>Sozomene</hi> in the third booke 5. chap. reporteth, that a Deacon of the Primitiue Church was depoſed for bauing beene tranſported with the like curioſity: and <hi>Gregory</hi> of Tours for the ſame occaſion blameth a ſon of <hi>Gontran,</hi> becauſe he had ſent to aske queſtions of a Pythoniſſe, ſo hee calleth a woman which had an euill ſpirit and Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith: <hi>Non licet Daemones adiurare per modum deprecationis, quia id ad beneuolentiam pertinet, qua non licet ad Daemones vti, ne ſocij Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num fiamus: licet tamen per virtutem diuini numinis eos adiurando eijcere, ne noceant, non autem vt ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid per eos diſcamus aut conſequamur: It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to adiure the diuels by way of deprecation, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, becauſe that is a token of good will, which wee may not beare vnto them, leaſt wee become companions of diuels: but it is lawfull by the vertue of God his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power by adiuration to caſt them out, that they doe no hurt, but not to learne or attaine any thing by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that which is moſt hainous and capitall by all lawes, to enquire of the health of the Prince, and of the ſecrets of Eſtate, theſe were the very tearmes: <hi>Quid circa ſanitatem regis, quid circa compoſitionem armorum inter regem, &amp; magnates ſubditos, quid circa vrbes obſidionales, quid circa bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum cum Hiſpanis, vel cum haereticis: How long the King ſhould liue, what ſhould come to paſſe as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the compoſition betweene the King and his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, what of the garriſon Townes, what concerning the warre with the Spaniards, or with the Heretikes.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8637:49"/>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, that it appertaineth not to anie man to enquire concerning the life of the Prince, but thoſe who haue ſome enterpriſe vpon his perſon, or who laie the foundation of ſome great hope vpon his death: and he which inſtructed a Mathematician, forbad him expreſly to meddle with the life of Kings, or with the Eſtate of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealths. <hi>Non enim oportet vt de ſtatu reipub. aliquid nefaria curioſitate diſcamus: For we ought not, neither is it lawful for vs by wicked curioſity to learne any thing concerning the Eſtate of the common-wealth.</hi> Kings to whom God hath giuen the gouernment of the Earth, to whom all power and dignities are ſubiect, participating immediately of the greatneſſe of God doe not depend on the courſe of the Planets, and ought not to fall into the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity of men. It is reſerued to God alone how long the life of a great King, or the peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of his Eſtate ſhall endure.</p>
            <p>As little had wee vnderſtood the propoſition and reſolution of <hi>Ioannes de Salas Caſtelanus Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elienſis</hi> in his commentaries which he hath made <hi>in primam ſecundam</hi> of Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> dedicated to <hi>Aquauiua</hi> their father Generall <hi>tractat.</hi> 8. <hi>diſput. v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica ſect.</hi> 5. neer the end, which is more dangerous for the ſetting wide open of Monaſteries, then the doctrine of heretikes; for making this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. <hi>Vtrum ſemper ſequi liceat opinionem, quaea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genti probabilior aut aequè probabilis apparet,</hi> behold his reſolution: <hi>Religioſus autem efficaciſsima debet habere motiua, vt probabiliter opinaretur, verameſſe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8637:50"/>reuelationem, qua ſecum diſpenſaret Deus, vt matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium contraheret, contra communem legem: hacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus enim Deus nunquam diſpenſauit: Si tamen veram probabilitatem haberet, poſſet ad euitanda magna in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoda, vti diſpenſatione dubia, &amp; tantum proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili, quod etiam in diſpenſationibus quorundam praela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum obſeruatum eſt. Whether it bee lawfull to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low alwaies the opinion which ſeemeth vnto the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker more probable or as probable as any other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his reſolution. That a Religious man ought to haue moſt powerfull motiues, that he may probably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture that the reuelation is true whereby God would diſpence with him to marry contrary vnto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law of marriage; for God neuer yet diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with any one: But if hee hath had any true probability he may, for auoiding of greater inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences vſe a diſpenſation though it be doubtfull and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly probable, which hath beene alſo obſerued in diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with certaine Prelates.</hi> From henceforth fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, oriſons and praiers will become vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to preſerue chaſtity, euery one will abuſe his reuelation, for to put in vre the euill paſſions of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>And indeed the precept was not long without an example: <hi>Menas</hi> the Ieſuite committed ſo ſcandalous an inceſt that hee was called in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for it in the inquiſition of <hi>Spaine;</hi> thoſe of his company by faining a miracle freed him from his puniſhment, which lighted vpon the officers at <hi>Valladolid,</hi> who were diſplaced for that peece of ſeruice: the ſcandale hereof is redoubled in the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8637:51"/>writings of <hi>Sanches</hi> and of <hi>Chetora,</hi> who are of the ſame ſociety, the onely imagination whereof is ſufficient to make a man looſe the knowledge of himſelfe and to become worſe then a beaſt.</p>
            <p>And like vnto this is that which is common in euery mans hand ſet forth ſome foure moneths agoe, to wit the ſermons made vpon the beatifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their father <hi>Ignacius,</hi> by the which the name of <hi>Ignacius</hi> is not onely equalled with that of our Sauiour and placed in parallell with it: but ſurrogated in his place: the miracles done in the name of the Almighty for exalting of his glorie, and the confuſion of Infidels, which we beleeue as an article of our faith, abaſed, diminiſhed, and diſtruſted. For to extoll thoſe of father <hi>Ignacius,</hi> I ſay not vncertaine, but altogether vntrue, and which neuer were, as they themſelues confeſſe, ſince that <hi>Pibadenera</hi> in the fift booke of his life ſaith thus of him, <hi>eius ſanctitatem minus teſtatam miraculis: that his ſanctitie was not ſo much teſtified by miracles,</hi> and as if they had commerce and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation with heretikes, from making him Gods Vicar, applying vnto him that of S. <hi>Paul: fungimur legatione pro Chriſto, wee are emploied in the meſſage of Chriſt,</hi> from calling him the miniſteriall head of the Church, they make him ſucceſſor vnto Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, ſtriking at his holy reſurrection, and the eternity of his raigne in the Church.</p>
            <p>O learned, o ſweet, o free antiquity how thou art faire with al thy wrinkles, with the lineaments of thy countenance defaced and hardly to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8637:52"/>O holy ſchoole of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> how perfect is the vertue of your mediocrity, inſpire into thy ſucceſſors the truth of the prophecie of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree verified in the yeere 1554. theſe are the words thereof, <hi>Societas haec periculoſa in negotio fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei: This ſocietie is dangerous in matter of faith,</hi> in this age corrupted with paſsion, and adulation let this truth find one mouth exempt from this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion: neither haue they failed; there cenſure and teſtimony conſtant and loyall vnto the truth ſhall euer be ſeene, and appeare notwithſtanding, the-threats, and inuectiues of the Ieſuits full of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being as ſo manybels of the <hi>Coribantes</hi> which ſerue to no other purpoſe but to trouble &amp; diſquiet the heads of thoſe who are leaſt ſtaied and ſetled.</p>
            <p>Let vs adde hereunto the inuention of their equiuocations, and diſsimulations, of their homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymies, which are deceipts of ſimilitude and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parence in ſtead of the thing it ſelfe, changing the ſubſtance without changing the name: which they confeſſe that they make vſe of, when they are to anſwere vnto Kings and Magiſtrates, and other perſons bearing office in the common-wealth, whoſe ſubiects they doe not beleeue they are, nor that they are iuſticiable by them, their words and their anſwers are like the images of <hi>Dedalus</hi> which deceiued the ſence, changing their viſage and countenance, as often as a man did caſt his eies vpon them. This inuention of aequiuocation reduced into an art, and recommended by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarrus</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:8637:52"/>in fauour of this ſociety, not only like vnto the artifice practiſed by <hi>Arrius,</hi> who after he had ſubſcribed vnto the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> ſware vnto another confeſſion of faith which hee had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his boſome, altogether different from that: but alſo vnto that law of the <hi>Manichees,</hi> which permitted them to anſwere quite contrary vnto that which was true indeed, and that which they perfectly knew, noted by <hi>Lucas Siculus</hi> in the time of the Emperour <hi>Baſil,</hi> and which he repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, ſetting it downe in theſe words: <hi>Iura periura ſceretum prodere noli.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By reaſon whereof, for to confirme their euill doctrines, then when there is any danger to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoided or aduantage to be taken, it is both law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and honourable to vſe this inuention, yea boldly to gaineſay that which they are moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of: witneſſe that which they haue done by the writing of <hi>Richeome,</hi> who making anſwere to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatory miniſtred vnto them which was thus: what they would do in caſe there ſhould be a Pope which after the example of <hi>Iulius</hi> the 2. ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly diſplay his cenſures againſt <hi>France?</hi> being vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, hee anſwered, <hi>That their ſociety would doe that which good Frenchmen then did, who defending their rights did not giue ouer the reſpect due vnto the holy Sea, did acknowledge the Pope to be the head only in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall matters, approuing the Councell of Tours of the yere</hi> 1510. <hi>held for the defence of the rights of Lewis the</hi> 12. Cardinal <hi>Bell.</hi> in the treatiſe which he hath made againſt the diuines of <hi>Venice,</hi> ſaith, that the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8637:53"/>meaning of <hi>Richeome</hi> was only to ſhew, that good French men ought to obey the Pope without debating the matter, and counſell the King to come to agreement with him, and not to reſiſt him by armes.</p>
            <p>This is the reaſon that all their declarations are conceiued in defectiue and incertaine words, to the end that they may diſaduow, reuoke or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe interpret them, when they ſhall thinke good: and that which is moſt intolerable, yea moſt vnchriſtianlike, they ground theſe cauillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſsimulations vpon textes of ſcripture, which they corrupt moſt licentiouſlie, as if God the father of truth, had taught the contrary to truth. And as it falleth out ordinarily, that the worſt getteth maſtery of that which is better: the vſage of their diſsimulations and cauillations doth inſenſibly creepe in, and men leauing ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and innocency, for to learne their ſhifts and euaſions, doe receiue the corruption thereof both in generall and in particular.</p>
            <p>And to the end that it may not be thought a particular vice of ſome one among them; but a precept generall to all their ſociety, <hi>Ribadenera</hi> in the life of father <hi>Ignacius</hi> the 3. booke and 11. chapter intituled, <hi>De prudentia rerum agendarum,</hi> hath written thus, <hi>Dicebat quibus artibus diabolus ad perniciem hominum vteretur, ijſdem nobis vten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ad ſalutem: nam vt ille cuiuſque naturam explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, &amp; animi propenſionem pertentans, ad eam ſe attemperat, vt ambitioſis ſplendida, vtilia cupidis, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuoſis</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:8637:50"/>
               <hi>luptuoſis iucunda, piis quaeſpeciem habent pietatis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit, &amp; non irrumpit ſubito, ſed ſenſim irrepit, &amp; in animaeſe familiaritatem inſinuat, penituſque tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem immergit: ſic ſpiritualis, ac peritus artifex, vniuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiuſque naturae conuenienter ſe debet gerere, &amp; in principio multa diſsimulare, in multis conniuere, dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps parta beneuolentia ipſos quibuſcum agit ipſorum armis expugnare: Hee ſaid that thoſe arts which the Diuel would vſe for mens deſtruction, the ſame muſt we vſe for their ſafety: for as hee ſearching out the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of euery man, and throughly conſidering the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the mind, doth applie himſelfe thereunto, ſo that he propoſeth vnto ſenſuall and voluptuous men pleaſant things, to the ambitious thoſe things which ſeeme glorious, to godly men ſuch things as haue a ſhew of pietie, and doth not ſuddainly breake in, but ſtealeth on, by little and little, and doth inſinuate himſelfe into the familiarity of the ſoule, and at laſt doth wholy diue into it: ſo he that is a cunning &amp; ſpiritual craftsmaſter ought to carry himſelfe agreeablie to the nature of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one, and at the beginning to diſſemble many things &amp; to winke at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; afterwards he hath gotten their good will to conquer thoſe whom he hath in hand with their owne weapons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue already ſhewed how by the doctrine of the ſpirituall Monarchie, abſolute and infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which teacheth Kings to obey, and to which the Ieſuits attribute the correction of Princes, that they are obliged to follow the Councell of the Pope in the gouernment of temporall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that in caſe of reſiſtance they may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8637:51"/>and after publike iudgement, that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man to attempt vpon their liues, and to kill them. By this word, of publique iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they meane the Pope, as ſoueraigne ouer all Common-wealths, and of all Chriſtian pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Behold their proofe by the ſaying of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zorius,</hi> whom they confeſſe to be one of the moſt modeſt amongſt them, in the ſecond party, the 11 booke 5. chapter of his morall inſtitution; after that he hath confirmed the power that the Pope hath to depoſe Kings, and ſought to anſwere the obiection of thoſe who ſay that it cannot be done contrary vnto the will of the people, hee addeth further in theſe tearmes: <hi>Tertiò obiicitur, populo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vito non poteſt Rex auferri aut dari: reſpondeo à Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano Pontifice Regem auferri, vel dari iuſtis de cauſis, &amp; tunc populus Romano Pontifici tanquam ſuperiori parere debet: Thirdly it is obiected that a King cannot be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor taken away againſt the wil of the people: to this I anſwere, that hee may vpon iuſt cauſe, and then the people ought to obey the Pope of Rome as their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence it enſueth that if a Prince doth enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize any thing in this Eſtate againſt the will of the Pope, if hee contradict this publike iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if he come to ſquare with any of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Bull <hi>In caena Domini,</hi> without deſiſting from it, that he is preſently a Tyrant, an vſurper and ſchiſmaticke, and as ſuch a one may be meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly ſlaine. By the articles of this Bull it is conteined amongſt other things, that all perſons who
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8637:53"/>who haue ſecret or publique alliance with here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, haue commerce with them, or doe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and protect them, are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, although they are not particularly deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, named nor ſpecified in the Bul, which is pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at <hi>Rome</hi> euery Thurſday before Eaſter, and then the Ieſuits teach, and their doctrine is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, that no other proceeding, nor no other iudgement is to be expected. According where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto <hi>Suares</hi> the moſt renowned of their ſocietie in the fourth Tome of his workes, and his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of cenſures, which he made expreſly againſt our King, diſput. 5. ſect. 6. ſaith, that ſubiects vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a morall certitude, which they ſhall haue that their Prince will doe anie thing contrary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Catholike religion, may without atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any iudgement or other cenſure of the Pope, rebell and take armes againſt him: theſe are his very words: <hi>Si ſubditi timeant ex eorum princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patu maximum periculum fidei &amp; religionis imminere: tunc enimiure defenſionis poſſunt eos repellere, &amp; obedientiam ac fidelitatem negare, quod facere poſsint, etſi non eſſent excommunicati, nec per Eccleſiam eſſent illis aliae poenaeimpoſitae, ſolum ob praedictum pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum. If the ſubiects feare that by their rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment faith and religion is like to incurre any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: then they may in defence thereof repell them and denie them obedience and fidelity, which they may doe although they were not excommunicated, nor had any other puniſhment inflicted vpon them by the Church, only for feare of the aforeſaid danger. Molina</hi> in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8637:54"/>his treatiſe <hi>de iuſtitia &amp; iure. Leſsius</hi> in the 2. booke <hi>De iuſtitia &amp; iure</hi> 9. chapter <hi>dubit.</hi> 4. ſay the like, and that it is lawfull to attempt vpon the life of thoſe Princes whom they call Tyrants, vpon the tacite will and intention or preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the common-wealth: <hi>Mens oppreſsae Reipub. eſt, vt á quouis etiam, qui non eſt pars Reip. defendatur, fi aliter liberari non poſsit. It is the mind and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the common-wealth which is oppreſſed, that it may be defended of any man, though he be no member thereof, if it cannot otherwiſe be freed.</hi> That which they call <hi>mens Reipub.</hi> the motion of <hi>Parricides, Mariana</hi> termeth, proceeding as it ſeemeth with more aduiſedneſſe, the counſell of graue and learned men: <hi>Viri eruditi &amp; graues in conſilium ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibeantur: Let the aduiſe and counſell of wiſe and grauemen be vſed.</hi> It is not to be doubted, whom he intendeth, this is as euident to his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Sun at midday vnto our eies, for his booke beareth the priuiledge and allowance of their Prouinciall deputed by their Generall: and behold the reaſon why they are neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned and no others: It is there in as much as the eſtabliſhment of the abſolute power aboue all Princes is their principall vow and deſire, they muſt haue the directing and executing of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes which ſerue to this end: ſo that in thoſe places where the inquiſition is not receiued, the Ieſuits exerciſe the office, and haue the ſecret charge thereof, and their Generall the direction: whence it proceedeth, that all their aduiſe, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8637:54"/>and directions doe make a part of this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like iudgement: ſo that in ſtead of ſpirituall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, moued with another ſpirit then that whereof they make ſhew, theſe are Officers ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing againſt Princes, for to ouerthrow their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; to ſubrogate that of the Pope in the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty &amp; the matter ſtanding thus, he that deſireth to be inſtructed in this learning, cannot addreſſe himſelfe to any but thoſe who handle it, and beſt vnderſtand it, as they cannot deny, but that this is the ſole and only intellect which animateth the whole Vniuers of their ſociety.</p>
            <p>And indeed they alone haue touched it in their ſermons: lightnings which went before, and were vnto our eies preſages of the tempeſts, wherewithall we all thought wee ſhould haue beene vtterly confounded. A curſed doctrine, which whether it bee written or ſpoken in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or ſecret, there is not any one touch thereof, which hath not beene as the point of a dagger at our heart.</p>
            <p>The King by his warres, labors, and victories had reeſtabliſhed with <hi>France</hi> all Chriſtendome, had obliged all Princes and people, the two third parts of the world had the Lilies grauen in their hearts, and thought themſelues intereſſed in his proſperity. <hi>France</hi> being in flouriſhing eſtate, neuer ſaw her ſelfe in better caſe to ſuccour her friends, her Prince was of immortall valour, of an admirably ſtrong complexion, whoſe felicity did dazell the eies of all his enemies: when the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8637:55"/>Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> moſt ſtrictly allied vnto this crowne did inſtantly deſire her helpe, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt the oppreſsion of the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> to which the Ieſuits are moſt deuoted: our King had not omitted any exhortation or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion whatſoeuer, to remoue the warre, and to cauſe that the matter in queſtion ſhould be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and decided in any other maner: knowing better then any other, that neceſsity alone can iuſtifie the armes of Chriſtians againſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and being not beleeued, he prepared for the liberty of <hi>Germany</hi> ſuch ſuccours, as his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, his honour, and his duty could not haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied.</p>
            <p>But willing before his departure to giue vnto <hi>France</hi> and vnto all the world the contentment of the coronation of the Queene, a Princeſſe crowned and adorned with all vertues, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry height of our beſt eſtate, of our greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>Extrema gaudij luctus occupat,</hi> ioy and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row lead one another by the hand: the King paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through the middeſt of his moſt affectionate City, amongſt his moſt faithfull ſeruants, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in maieſtie, was ſtroke in the ſide with a knife of the ſame temper that thoſe of <hi>Clement, Barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere,</hi> and <hi>Chaſtell</hi> were of, his heart was preſently in a ſwound, ſtifled in his blood, what? are there to be found any minds ſo vnnaturall, ſo diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call as to conſpire, as to attempt the death of a Prince ſo behouefull, ſo amiable, vnto his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, ſo equitable vnto his neighbors, ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8637:55"/>for all Chriſtendome? There was not time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to bring him backe to the Louure, before his eies were ſetled in his head, his lips pulled vp within his fleſh, his blood clotted like ice in his beard: can we thinke on it a quarter of an houre without pulling out our heart? he which filled all with his power, this ſoule of the world, this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterpeece &amp; wonder of nature, this valiant warlike hand, falleth, and is taken from vs without any other warre then that of this doctrine, by the hand of the moſt hideous, moſt cruell, and moſt fearefull monſter that euer was vpon the earth, by a more then helliſh and infernall furie.</p>
            <p>Let any man reade the confeſsions of <hi>Barriere</hi> and of <hi>Chaſtel,</hi> let them bee confronted with the anſweres of this execrable parricide, there is not any difference at all betweene them: the markes of this doctrine doe viſibly appeare therein; <hi>That the King was a tyrant and fauoured heretickes againſt the will of the Pope, who was God vpon earth, that the Preachers had ſufficiently explained the cauſe which had moued him to doe it.</hi> Stupide and bloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh fellow, it is true, and why ſhould it be diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled? in all other points concerning this ſubiect he had ſubtilties and euaſions, and was very cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therein, you haue heretofore vnderſtood as much, Maſter <hi>Iohn Filleſac</hi> a worthy Curate of the Pariſh of Saint <hi>Iohn:</hi> Maſter <hi>Philip de Gamache</hi> the Kings Profeſſor in diuinity another Iſraelite, <hi>Coeffeteau</hi> heretofore Prior of the <hi>Iacobines,</hi> all diuines of great merite can witneſſe it, and hee of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8637:56"/>their owne companie, who confeſſed him, better then any other, who put him in minde of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and bad him take heed of accuſing thoſe who were innocent.</p>
            <p>Alas! you were a thouſand times more ſecure, you Emperors and Kings enemies of Chriſtians, who amongſt the greateſt perſecutions which the Church endured, in the middeſt of the great and frequent martyrs which ſuffered by your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and commandement haue ſeene no other weapon nor defence, then that of praier, of oriſons, of praiſe and thankſgiuing, but that of teares, as <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> witneſſeth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that any of thoſe who truly adored Ieſus Chriſt, yea, in the hotteſt of all their torments and perſecutions, once thought either in word or deed, I doe not ſay to make any attempt vpon your perſons, but to be the cauſe of the leaſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or leaſt commotion of your Eſtate. O Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of peace, doctrine of ſweetneſſe and charitie, to what vſe are you emploied? what aduantage is giuen to Infidels and miſcreants to continue their hate againſt the Church, in ſtead of louing it, what coales of Gods diuine vengeance do you pull vpon your heads?</p>
            <p>O <hi>France,</hi> how farre different was the cenſure of your innocent ſchoole the yeeres immediatelie precedent, when your King <hi>Henry</hi> the 2 vpon the ſelfe ſame ſubiect, and to deliuer <hi>Germany</hi> from the vſurpation which <hi>Charles</hi> the fift would haue made vnder colour of religion, did leade ſixtie
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8637:56"/>thouſand French men all Catholiques euen vnto the <hi>Rhene,</hi> and ſo farre, that he made him giue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his booty: can we learne out of the hiſtory of any one Diuine in thoſe daies, or one ſubiect which thought himſelfe leſſe obliged vnto his Prince, or which bare him leſſe affection for that cauſe? And yet 6. yeeres before our very do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> had framed articles for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the hereſie of the Lutherances inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the body of our ordinances, and vpon the which the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> laid the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall foundation of the reſolutions concerning that doctrine: but the ſchoole of the Ieſuits had not yet taught nor publiſhed, that Kings might be depoſed vpon any ſecret intention, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. He whom God had moſt viſibly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, who did obſcure the memory of the moſt fortunate and happy Monarchs, the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſacred perſon of all Chriſtendome, to whom the holy Sea was beholding for the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, it enioyeth, the holy father for his quiet and repoſe: he who had renounced the ſafetie of his owne, to endeare you vnto him, who made the clemency of his iuſtice to triumph in fauour of you, receaued ſo ill a recompence for his boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and goodneſſe, by your doctrine: a doctor of the Church ſaid that it was in the power of God to pardon a Virgin defiled, but not to reſtore her to her virginity: euen ſo fareth it with your fidelity and allegeance towards Princes after you haue once made your vowes vnto your Generall.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:8637:57"/>
            <p>The inſpirations and viſions with which theſe vndertakers ſay the are poſſeſſed, are they not the inuentions and ſubtilties of this doctrine, for to corrupt and peruert the mindes of men, and to transforme the diſpoſitions of their vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and will, to the end that the fantaſie and apprehenſion which they haue taken, may the more eaſily be ſo imprinted in their imagination, that they may neuer receiue any other? The letter of <hi>William Criton</hi> the Ieſuite, vſed by <hi>Riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome,</hi> in his Apologeticall complaint, for to couer the doctrine of this ſociety, by the which it is maintained, that it is lawfull for particular men to kill thoſe whom they call Tyrants, ſaieth, that this is not permitted, if thoſe priuate men haue no reuelation or viſion, which perſwadeth them thereunto: who ſhall be witneſſe of this viſion or reuelation but himſelfe? and ſo by this meanes he may take permiſſion both to kill and iuſtifie the murther from himſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is reported in the hiſtories of Aſſaſins &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, that they were ſo corrupted, &amp; <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Tours</hi> toward the end of his fourth booke ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe who killed King <hi>Sigiſbert,</hi> ſaith, that they were inueagled, and inchaunted, <hi>maleficiati:</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the epiſtle 165. vnto <hi>Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſaith, that the Donatiſts, moſt dangerous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, did induce their followers to many villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies by viſions, and continuing his diſcourſe in the epiſtle 168. reporteth the example of a yong man, who by the counſell of the like viſion had
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8637:57"/>killed his mother. The minde of a man is like vnto a looking glaſſe, which doth vſuallie repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that which is ſhewed vnto it, ſpecially when it is directed vnto the moſt ſenſible part which is the conſcience: let vs adde moreouer that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide theſe fantaſies and inſpirations which ſerue to tranſport the feebleneſſe of theſe mindes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all diſcretion, they giue to theſe conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors crownes of martyrdome: and to proue this, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath highly commended <hi>Iames Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> for this quality, <hi>Mariana</hi> calleth him <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae decus aeternum,</hi> they doe the like by <hi>Guignard</hi> and <hi>Garnet,</hi> falſly attributing miracles vnto them.</p>
            <p>Call to mind, My Lords, if you pleaſe that which hath paſſed before your eies, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory whereof it ſeemeth is not yet buried: one named <hi>Charles Ridicoue</hi> a religious <hi>Iacobin</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> ſtirred vp by the preaching of the Ieſuites, who commended <hi>Iames Clement</hi> ordinarily as a Saint, and <hi>Chaſtel</hi> as a Martyr, hauing at vnawares giuen out ſpeeches whereby he teſtified that he had beene tickled with the like deſire, preſentlie his Prouinciall was commanded to bring him to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where he was promiſed wonders, both for the diſcharge of his conſcience, (for he had ſome remorce to attempt vpon the perſon of a moſt Catholique King, which held good corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencie with the Pope,) and alſo in regard of recompence both to himſelfe, his mother, and brother; he was viſited by father <hi>Hodume</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:8637:58"/>who gaue aduiſe whether he were of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of ſtrength, and reſolution ſufficient to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſuch a buſineſſe, in the end all fitting to the purpoſe, he had inſtruction to change his name, to alter his apparell, to learne to ride, daunce and fence, that he might be the more ready, and the ſooner haue admittance, theſe are the confeſſions made in this Parliament, by himſelfe who came thriſe into <hi>France,</hi> with this purpoſe and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He could giue you no reaſon why he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned the grace and pardon that was at the firſt offered him, nor why he came the ſecond time hauing beene formerly ſuſpected, nor why he perſeuered in his villanous deſigne, but that if the Ieſuits had perceaued or miſtruſted that hee had diſcloſed the ſecret of his enterprize, they would neuer haue forgiuen him, as they neuer reueale the confeſſions of ſuch people, be it anie enterprize whatſoeuer, or come what euill ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by it. At the very time of the laſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and execution of this <hi>Ridicoue</hi> ordeined by your decree of the moneth of Aprill 1599. was publiſhed and imprinted the booke of <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana;</hi> for to ſhew how conſtant the effects of their doctrine are, they prepare and faſten together iointly both the doctrine and the effects; and notwithſtanding one of them in his Apologie, hath written, that it had beene to be wiſhed that the laſt parricide had read it well ouer, becauſe it is conformable vnto the doctrine of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> which hath condemned the booke of <hi>Mariana,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:8637:58"/>and holdeth it to bee abhominable, together with the impoſture of the Apology: ſo bold and impudent are they to circumuent the truth with falſhood and deceit.</p>
            <p>Great and vnimitable King, the wiſdome of whoſe counſels and diligence in executing them, whoſe ſoundneſſe of iudgement more then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, we haue all equally admired, receiue in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of our affection, and for a ſure pledge of our faithfull ſeruice, our teares, our lamentations, our ſorrowes, our ſighs, and perpetuall mourning, which we offer vp vnto your glory. Happy ſoule made Citizen of heauen, and placed in the ranke of Angels in eternall reſt, farre from the care of warres, your roiall qualities and perfections ſhall bee euer written in our hearts, your name ſhall be for euer in our mouthes, and although that our cries are imperfect, that our voice interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſighs cannot vtter it ſelfe, that ſorrow bereaueth vs of our ſoules, and that there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no ſtrength in vs, but only to feele our griefe, wee will die rather then corrupt the holie law of your Eſtate, vnder whoſe Sunne ſince we liue, wee will for euer loue the light and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof.</p>
            <p>With the ſame teares and voice halfe dead, wee humbly beſeech the holy father, to enter into compaſsion of Chriſtendome, torne in peeces by this doctrine, and to remember what danger there is in taking from the ſpiritualtie the true honor and glory, by medling with the temporall
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8637:59"/>and ciuill gouernment, theſe are things which God would haue to bee wholly ſeparated and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct: that he will bee pleaſed to remember the wholeſome aduertiſement of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this abſolute power, which was then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to bee brought into the Church, in his 2. booke <hi>de conſid.</hi> chapter 6. <hi>I ergo tu &amp; tibiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpare aude, aut dominans apoſtolatum aut apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus dominatum, plane ab alterutro prohiberis, ſi vtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſimul habere voles, perdes vtrumque: Goe then and vſurpe if thou dare, being a publique Magiſtrate, the office of an Apoſtle, or being an Apoſtle the authoritie of the Magiſtrate, thou ſhalt plainely bee prohibited from enioying either, if thou wilt haue both together thou ſhalt looſe both.</hi> God hath prouided for the conſeruation and augmentation of his Church, by other remedies, and raiſed vp Biſhops, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and Paſtors from time to time: yet againe once more to bethinke himſelfe in this declining age of the world, how pernicious this exceſſe is; wee haue ſeene two of our Catholique Kings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to haue oppoſed their armies againſt thoſe of the Turke, to preſerue the Church and the reſt of the world from the inuaſion of Barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Infidels, brought vnto an vntimely death by reaſon of this doctrine, this great Eſtate the cheefeſt of Chriſtendome in danger of ruine: that he will protect the Church and vs from thoſe furious Empiriques, which hazard their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent remedies indifferently vpon all ſorts of men, without regarding the Eſtate of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8637:59"/>that he will purge and rid the world for euer of theſe ſo tragicall examples: <hi>France</hi> is nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and trained vp in a ſingular deuotion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward your holineſſe, towards the holy Sea, ſhee can neuer faile therein, the profeſsion of our ſchoole remaineth alwaies entire and inuiolable to the Chriſtian ſaith, and to the obedience due vnto the holie Sea: and as his ſucceſsion in the Popedome is not farre diſtant in time from that of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. ſo let it ſucceed it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting his mildneſſe and prudence, &amp; that he will be pleaſed to caſt his eie vpon this ſociety, which, vnder the pretext of the good of the Church, doth point at it one particular greatnes, to the which in the end it will vnite that of the Church, and they alreadie are not farre from it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the reaſons of the oppoſition which the Vniuerſity propoſeth againſt the letters ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Ieſuits, founded vpon the ſoueraign authority engrauen from all antiquity in the braſſe of the fundamentall lawes of the French monarchy, vpon her particular policy, vpon your decrees and vpon her holy and conſtant doctrine, which faſteneth the crowne to the head of kings, contrary vnto that of the Ieſuits, who attribute vnto the Pope a like ſuperiority ouer our kings, as ouer the leaſt Prieſts, or his moſt inferiour Officers &amp; vicars, yea far greater; maketh Kings to be but at wil, ſubiect to be depoſed &amp; killed fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nded more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer vpon ſo many miſerable examples which gall vs, and make vs feele the ſmart ſo particularly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:8637:60"/>that there is not any man who loueth the Eſtate, or Religion, which hath not had a feeling and apprehenſion thereof. The inſtruction of youth is not a matter of ſmall importance, in ancient time men had a ſpeciall care thereof next imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after that of Religion: children owe their ſife vnto their parents, but that they liue well, they owe that vnto thoſe who inſtruct them: and he doth no leſſe profit the Common-wealth who frameth and faſhioneth men well affected to the Eſtate, who nouriſheth them vnder the hope of honors and dignities, with reuerence vnto the lawes of the Country, then he who ſerueth in greater place with duty and fidelity: The Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of <hi>Paris</hi> hath hereof, loyally and worthily acquited and diſcharged her ſelfe theſe 8. hundred yeeres, neuer bound her ſelfe to any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, but to the honor of God, of her King, and to the good of the Church; Ill doctrine is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded, and that which is falſe, conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto the darkeneſſe which enuironneth vs in our corruption: there is (ſaith the wiſe man,) ſtore of gold and pearles, but lips that preſerue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that is a rare moueable. What father is there which had not rather looſe his life, honor, goods, and whatſoeuer hee hath elſe moſt deare in this world, then to nouriſh one who ſhall bee a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to his Country? Haue we not had intelligence within theſe three weekes of the conference held at <hi>Toul</hi> in <hi>Lorraine</hi> amongſt men impoiſoned with this doctrine, diſcloſed by an Hermite,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8637:60"/>wherein after declaration of their euill minde towards all Catholike Princes, it was agreed as granted amongſt them, that the Ieſuits had by their doctrine ſo cleared theſe maximes, that they ought to be held for ratified, and confirmed, in ſtead that they ought to be condemned, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed not only in the effects, but in the very dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt and moſt profound thoughts.</p>
            <p>They offer to ſubmit themſelues vnto the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Vniuerſity, and demand to be incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated: from the yeere 564. they haue done as much, and they are yet to beginne, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to renounce their vowes, faculties, Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, yea themſelues, we haue ſeene our ſelues cleane fruſtrated of this expectation, and to be the example of their power, and attempts contrarie vnto publike Order: in the yeere 1591. they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed not to meddle any more with affaires of Eſtate, it was then that they were moſt buſily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied in them, and embraced the world moſt greedily: they know well how to boaſt of this ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſince that they haue written in French, that their laie brethren could reade lectures therein to the Chancellour and greateſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> God knoweth whether in <hi>Spaine</hi> (if it be true that the ſermons were made there) they haue forgotten to enter into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon with our greateſt magiſtrats: there is not any one condition of their reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they haue not already tranſgreſſed and broken, by breues and letters obtained by tricks and vpon aduantages: it would be a ſtrange
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:8637:61"/>follie in vs, nay rather a great crime, to bee the firſt alwaies who are ſurpriſed, and the laſt to free our ſelues, to be ſo often abuſed and mocked by thoſe who beare two hearts in one breaſt, who for to make their doctrine to be receiued, are ſo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious as to impoſe and lay imputations vpon the Apoſtles themſelues, and to impute vnto them that lewd vice of coſinage and diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they vſe ordinarily; for <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his treatiſe concerning the exemption of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall men chap. 30. ſaith that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the Apoſtles haue preached obedience to the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike magiſtrate, &amp; that euery ſoule ſhould bee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto the Prince, only for to eſtabliſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; to giue the Goſpell paſſage: they will promiſe and ſweare to all conditions, ſince that by their owne proper conſtitutions they can be bound by nothing, to the end that they may make thoſe to be receiued which they would impoſe, by reaſon of the Pope his abſolute authority, without the which their ſociety cannot ſubſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> after the death of her King, hath placed her hope in the Queene, it is ſhee that giueth her life and nouriſhment: a Princeſſe whom ſtrangers admire, and the ſubiect honoreth, you haue found all the Princes furniſhed with great ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, tied with the ſame band of affection to the good and greatneſſe of this Eſtate. This magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Court of Peeres, the Diall of <hi>France,</hi> which hath alwaies ſhewed his Meridionall line, and the Officers of the Crowne, ready to doe their duty,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:8637:61"/>and to follow the high waie of honour, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and gentry, the Townes and people readie to ſacrifice themſelues, for to perform your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: continue on by your bounty and iuſtice, in making it appeare, that theſe were the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of our late King your huſband, which gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Monarchy, and to cauſe this liuely picture to be adored in his death, that the lawes of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the King your ſonne, may remaine by your wiſdome ſo ordered, that euery one may therein find his goods, his life, his honor, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in ſafetie and repoſe; ſo may the Counſell and prudence of the two great eies of this Eſtate alwaies watch ouer the affaires: perſeuere in this beliefe, that diuiſion and ciuill warre is the onelie deſolation of this great Empire: there is nothing which can diſturbe it but theſe extractors and Alchymiſts, which haue found out the meanes to diſſolue all piety, &amp; the moſt ſtrong &amp; naturall bands of affection: they eaſily can doe it with their ſeedes and dewes of ſermons, and confeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by the precepts of their learning, by meanes whereof they can peruert the courſe of nature altering our eſſence, and reaching the euill, which afterwards men fall into vnawares: they ſay that our ſoile is ſoft, that in one yeere they haue taken notice of all our humors, that they haue already procured of their ſide the vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed weakneſſe of woman and children, that wee are men little ſpeculitiue, who will bee quickly carried away, that wee are ready and eaſie
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:8637:62"/>to be moued, that they need not but a little to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, and ſet their affaires on foot, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they roule of themſelues, and flie on, as faſt as they can, to the very height of all exceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homer</hi> ſaith, that a ſword once vnſheathed draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men on by ſome ſecret inſtinct to deſignes not thought of, and ſeldom is guided by the diſcourſe of wiſdome and diſcretion: this is a <hi>criſis,</hi> vpon the which all Chriſtendome doth ſet her eies. Needeth there any greater proofe or confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this which wee haue ſaid, then the treatiſe newly compoſed by Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the abſence of our Sunne, by the which lifting vp his diſguiſe, hee vſeth no longer the terme of correction, it is not for hereſie or crime that he maintaineth that the Pope may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate and depoſe Kings, but vpon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſubiect it pleaſeth him if hee ſee that the good of the Church require it, <hi>de principe facere non principem: of a prince to make him no prince,</hi> and that he hath this power not only ouer Kingdoms, but ouer all that which apperteineth vnto either Chriſtians, heretikes, ſchiſmatikes, or ſcandalous people in what ſort ſoeuer, if they wil not yeeld &amp; ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus vnto his propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which being granted their concluſions are ineuitable. Do they not write that there is a new ſect of Catholiques Roiall, as if to loue the King and to be a good Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike were things contrary one to the other and incompatible: he particularly repenteth that for modeſty ſake hee hath ſometime auowed,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8637:62"/>that Eccleſiaſticall men as ſubiects, owe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto Princes, now he confidently affirmeth; <hi>Clericos principibus Ethnicis ſolo facto nullo iure fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſse ſubditos: That Eccleſiaſticall men were ſubiect vnto heathen Princes, onely in fact and not of right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, this doctrine is the open deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the authority of Kings and of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the ſubuerſion of all the Eſtates of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the cypher and ſtrange character where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they holde correſpondence with all that which is either corrupted or corruptible.</p>
            <p>In the eſtate wee now ſtand, the Ieſuits cannot haue a greater obſtacle then to be bound, ſtrictly to obſerue the conditions of their reeſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to bring them thereunto, to make them ſubiect vnto Magiſtrates, and ordinary powers as other Religious men are, without ſuffering their enterprizes; to maintaine and keepe the Biſhops, Prelates and Curates in their dignities, againſt whom they ſet themſelues, as they doe againſt all other Eccleſiaſticall perſons: not to permit them to haue the inſtruction of youth, to the end that inſtitution and learning come not vnder their monopoly, and that henceforward it ſtrengthen it ſelfe in ſuch ſort that a man muſt leaue to be a Frenchman for to become a Ieſuite: and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to haue a care, that men doe not abandon, nor forſake the authority of our doctrine, which is the foundation of loue and fidelity to the Roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dignitie, for to receiue the inſtructions of this new diuinity framed and compoſed for the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8637:63"/>and reſpect of their particular greatneſſe, and authority, wherewithall they would adde to our beleefe this 13. article of faith, that all Crownes do depend of the Pope, and are held of him, who may depoſe Kings at his pleaſure, and aboue all the French Kings, ſo that our King ſhould by this meanes finde his Crowne worſe then it was left him, and receiue this preiudice during his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority.</p>
            <p>Our King, who growing vp and proſpering, ſhall learne the noble and valiant deeds of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his vertues, being the ornament and honour of Kings, whoſe glory ought to beginne and ende with the praiſe of his name, he ſhall inherite his proweſſes, and being come yong to this actiue art of managing a Kingdome, inſtructed by the ſage counſels of his mother, ſhall bee reuerenced as <hi>Salomon</hi> for his wiſdome, and ſerue for a new miracle to all the world, and to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God for our ſinnes not hauing permitted that our great King, of whom we were not worthie, ſhould continue amongſt vs his yeeres ſhining with all vertues, nor peaceably end the courſe of his life which remained; let vs all wiſh and deſire with our heart and with affection, that it would pleaſe the diuine bounty to confirme according to his deſerts, and as it is greatly behoofefull and expedient for <hi>France,</hi> the aſſurance of this our greateſt happineſſe, conſiſting in the perpetuall continuance of his roiall progenie, for the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, greatneſſe and authority whereof, the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> from the Temple of the <hi>Muſes,</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:8637:63"/>where this great <hi>Hercules</hi> doth now make his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, doth the third time aduertiſe you of the tempeſt, wherwith the Ieſuits threaten the calme of <hi>France:</hi> and if it happen, which God forbidde, that our preſages and aduertiſements be yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, we ſhall haue this contentment, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony in allſucceeding ages, that with the truth of the holy doctrine, wherein we haue alway con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, we haue not failed to performe the dutie and affection we owe vnto our King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</p>
            <p>The Vniuerſity concludeth, humbly praying, that the Ieſuits now demandants bee denied the effect and allowance of their letters, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that they be prohibited from reading, teaching, or vſing any other cholaſticall function in the Vniuerſity.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:8637:64"/>
               <head>The Order meane before iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>vpon the arguments of both parties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Court vpon the allowance of the letters doth order that the Counſell of both parties ſhal amend their pleadings, and adde whatſoeuer they ſhal think fit within 8. daies, they ſhal pleade in Barre, or reply within the time appointed by the order for the hearing of iudgement: doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the Prouincia, and thoſe of his company demandants, ſhall forthwith ſubſcribe the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion made by their Prouinciall, to conforme themſelues to the doctrine of the ſchoole of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> and principally in that which concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the conſeruation of the ſacred perſons of Kings, the maintenance of their regall authority, and the liberties of the French Church, from all time and antiquity kept and obſerued in this Realme, and that all ſhall be viewed and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated vnto the King his ſolliciter generall, and annexed vnto the determination and decree of the Court. In the meane time hath inhibited, and doth inhibite and forbidde the demandants to make any innouation, or to doe or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8637:64"/>any thing contrary vnto the letters of their reeſtabliſhment, and in preiudice of them, and of the decree verifying the ſame, or to intermeddle by themſelues, or any other perſons in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, with the inſtruction of youth in this Citie of <hi>Paris</hi> in any ſort whatſoeuer, or there to vſe anie ſcholaſticall function, or exerciſe, vpon paine of looſing the benefit of their reeſtabliſhment, which hath beene aſſented vnto, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing coſtes. Made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 22. of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> 1611.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
